All right guys.
Welcome back.
This is Angela from The App Brewery,
and in this module we're going to be making something really awesome.
We're moving upwards in the world and we're going to be building much much cooler web sites.
So, in order to teach you about some of the more intermediate / advanced parts of the Document Object Model
or the DOM, I wanted to show you how you can build this drum kit web site.
So by the end of this module you would have not only understood how to add event listeners to buttons
and keystrokes so that you'll know when the user is tapping on the keyboard or clicking on a particular
button on your web site and you can respond to it,
but you also end up with this awesome web site that you can impress all of your friends with.
So the way that this works is that we've got a number of keys here that represent different drums in
a typical drum set.
And when you click on any of these buttons then you'll get the corresponding sound of the drum.
And in addition you can also use the keys on the keyboard.
So now every time I crack a terrible programming joke, I'll be able to give you a drum roll.
So I hope you're ready.
It's going to be really exciting.
Let's get started in the next lesson.