All right, so now that we're ready and we're prepped, it's time to turn our locally developed and hosted,
dbank and put it onto the live Internet computer network where you'll see it gets a URL that ends
with ic0.app.
To get started, head over to faucet.dfinity.org and then click on the button to authorize
the faucet using your GitHub account.
So you'll need to log in on GitHub. Now in order to prevent people from abusing the cycles
faucet, because after all, you sort of getting free resources, they've added a limitation where the
GitHub account has to be aged.
So it has to have been created over 90 days ago.
That means you can't just create one now and be able to get more cycles.
And this is why I'm saying when we're doing the deploy, we have to be ultra-careful so we don't waste
our cycles.
In addition, the GitHub account has to be active over the last 30 days. And if you matched all of
that criteria and you log in, then you should be able to proceed to step two, where they want your principal
ID.
Now the principal is basically a generic identifier.
It will refer to an entity that can be authenticated by the Internet computer blockchain, so that
can be a user like yourself or simply a canister.
So the first time that you actually use the definitive canister SDK, it will automatically create a
default developer identity for you.
And this includes the principal.
So this principal ID or the principal identifier is basically associated with your developer identity.
It's used to identify you and allows you to control canisters or control applications that you build.
And in our case, it will be used to determine where these free cycles are going to go.
So in order to find the principal ID, let's go ahead and copy this command and paste it into a new
terminal.
Once you've gotten that ID back, then copy it entirely and paste it into the box there.
Next, we're going to generate a new cycles wallet.
So click on that and click Continue.
And then finally, it's going to take a few seconds to set up everything behind the scenes.
And then once that's done, it'll show you your balance in terms of terra cycles.
So this is 15 terra cycles that I've got, which currently is equivalent to about $20.
Now, remember that you can't actually convert this back to real money
unfortunately. It's not like a token, like the ICP token where it's freely exchanged and traded.
This can only be used to power our canisters on the internet computer blockchain.
So now that we've got our free cycles, the final thing to do is to copy this command and to set the ID
of our default wallet.
And in order for this to work, we first have to make sure that we cd over to our dbank project.
And then once you cded over, go ahead and simply paste that command into the terminal and then it should
do a bunch of things until it tells you that your wallet has been set successfully.
And now that you're all set, it's time to check our balance.
And to do this, we need to copy the ID that we got previously when we connected our wallet and then
we need to add .raw.ic0.app.
And once you head over there, it's going to ask you to authorize yourself.
And in order to do this, we have to create what's called an Internet identity anchor.
Basically, this is similar to a login with Google, a log in with Facebook, but in this case, we're
logging in with our Internet identity.
So in order to create this, let's first provide a name for our device, and then it's going to ask
us, how do you want to verify your identity?
If you have a USB security key, then choose that.
But otherwise just use this device.
And this way you will verify with the password that you used to log on. And once you confirm, it's going
to give you an internal identity
anchor, so make sure you write this down and keep a hold of this because you won't be able to get hold
of it if you lose it and you won't be able to authenticate yourself with your wallet with all your cycles.
So that could be a big problem.
So write it down now on a piece of paper, back it up, save it somewhere where you won't forget and
then you can click Continue.
It's a good idea to set up a recovery mechanism now in case you forget your anchor. So you can choose
the seed phrase if you don't have a security key.
And it's going to give you a whole bunch of words which you're going to need to write down again, maybe
offline, so that nobody can get access to it through the Internet.
Now, finally, once you're done with that, click the continue button and then we can register the
device.
So copy the code here and then type it into the terminal.
And once that's done, if you hit refresh, you should be able to see your cycles represented on this
website.
You can see at the moment I've got 14 terra cycles and it shows who are the principals who control
this wallet. And later on,
once we start deploying, you'll see the canisters that's created from this wallet as well.
That's all it takes to tap into the faucet and get some of these free cycles.
But now that we have our cycles, in the next lesson, we're going to use them to deploy our dbank application
to the live Internet computer blockchain.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you in the next lesson.