Hi, guys.
This is Angela from the brewery and I'm so excited to be doing this first ever live AMA.
So for those of you guys who've been with me for the longest, you know that back in the days in the
courses we used to do these live Ask Angela anythings and this is trying to bring it back and see how
you guys are all doing while you're safely at home.
And yeah, so I've never really done anything like this, so I'm a little bit nervous, but hopefully
it's going to go great and I'm going to get to know some more of you guys.
All right.
So the plan is we're going to take a look at some of the questions that were asked ahead of time.
So over the last week, you guys have been posting your questions on the ask page and our team has compiled
a bunch of the most upvoted questions.
So we're going to tackle some of those and then we're going to tackle some of these YouTube questions
live.
And I don't see too much of a delay in the chat, so hopefully I'll be able to get to you and we can
do a little bit of back and forth.
So.
All right, so here we've got the question from Melissa Santos.
So I'm just going to answer it all over again, because it seemed like when I went to the slides, you
couldn't hear me anymore.
So let's try this again.
So her question is how do you manage to use different languages for different projects without mixing
up the syntax?
All right.
So the first thing I want to say is that I mix up the syntax all the time, especially when I'm working
on like a swift project for a long time.
And then I switched to maybe doing a web development project with JavaScript.
Then, you know, I'm going to be missing semicolons.
I'm going to be just not writing JavaScript code.
But the great thing is that there's good lenders and if you use a good code editor like Atom of Yes
code or Sublime, then they should be able to pick up these things for you.
So I kind of let the machine do the machine part and then I do the brain pod, which is the logic.
That's the hardest part.
And the first part of her question she actually asked, so is is it a good idea to become fluent in
one language before moving on to other languages?
Now, I think this really depends on what you're trying to do, right?
If you're trying to build if your end project is an iOS app, then yeah, you definitely, definitely
need to get really good at probably Swift first.
But if you're trying to do something that occasionally requires just a little bit of web development
skills or just a little bit of maybe like a flutter multi iOS and Android app, then you could just
dive into the thing that you need.
The way I always see it is these programming languages.
They're not like a subject, they're not like history or geography.
They're more like a tool.
Like you're learning how to use the hammer, you're learning how to use a saw.
You don't have to get to like 100% of hammer ability before you can move on to the next tool.
It all depends on what you're trying to build, right?
All right.
So let's move on to the next question.
So in this question we've got from Jp RD and he's asking, given that coronavirus has affected so many
people and a lot of people are looking for ways of working from home, working remotely online, does
that mean that all the jobs are going to be filled up pretty quickly and, you know, it will be far
more competitive?
And I think I would say that, you know, you have to remember that when anything is desirable, it
is going to be competitive.
So if you think it's a great idea to work from home and, you know, have the flexibility of where you
live, be able to work remotely, then somebody else is going to have that idea as well.
But then again, you know, things that are worth doing are probably worth competing for.
It all depends on what is your ultimate goal.
And if your goal is to get a job as a web developer or as an app developer, then you just go to focus
on that goal and don't worry so much about what how much competition there is or how many other people
are applying to the same thing.
I mean, I remember back in the days when.
So I don't know if you guys know this, but I trained as a medical doctor and I worked as a doctor training
in orthopedic surgery for a number of years.
And when I was in medical school, even from like day one, people were telling me that if you want
to become a surgeon, like the chances are something like one in like 1000.
It's just so competitive.
And then within surgery, there's, you know, different competition ratios.
Like if you want to do brain surgery, that's like the most competitive field because there's only so
few brain surgeons.
But if you want to do, I don't know, maybe another type of surgery, maybe it's less competitive.
So I think even from that point, I was trained upon this idea that competition is just a way of life.
You know, you want something, other people want something, and then you just got to focus on yourself.
There's a really great book by Carl Newport, which I really like called So Good, They Can't Ignore
You.
I think that's the title anyways.
And I mean, the thing is, you don't really have to read the book.
I mean, it's a good book, but basically most of it is in the title like become so good at whatever
it is you do that they can't ignore you.
And they could be your boss, they could be a recruiter, they could be anybody, really.
And this is really something that I've always kept in my mind.
Like I've just tried to focus on doing the best job I can, and that means focusing on the student experience,
like, how can I make a course that is going to be the most helpful, the most enjoyable and the most
completed, right?
So I focus on these things and I don't really think about what other people are doing.
And that means that I have a product that I created and it's just much easier for me to think this way
if I spend all my time thinking about, well, you know, so-and-so is doing this or that person is
doing that, then I'm just going to be copying everybody all the time.
And if you guys have taken my courses, you know, that's usually not the way to go.
I mean, that also means that there's a lot of bad jokes in there that are untested and nobody's sanctioned.
And it's probably not a good idea.
But, you know, hey, we've got to try things right.
All right.
Let's move on to the next question.
So this question is from Mayank Saini.
I hope I pronounce that.
Okay.
I think I'm just going to be murdering people's names because I'm going to be bad at pronouncing eating.
So Mayank says a number of things.
My question is, how can I get a job as a full stack web developer to my dream company?
What do I have to master to do so?
Okay.
So your goal is to get a job as full stack web developer.
Now, some of you guys watching, maybe your goal is to get a job as an iOS developer.
Maybe you want to work as a data scientist.
Maybe you want to work at Facebook, Apple, Google, whatever it may be.
But the great thing is you already got your goal.
Like this is the first step because there are so many people I talked to who don't even know what they
want.
So you're already one step ahead of other people.
So now that you know what you want to get, how do you get them?
Well, let's think about it from the other point of view.
Let's say that you're a company.
Let's say you're a manager at Google and you want to hire a web developer.
Well, if you were the one who is doing the interview, who is sifting through all of the applications,
what would you think about?
This is a really, really useful exercise.
And this is something that I really it took it took some growing up to actually understand this, because
when you think about it from the other person's perspective, you know, they're not trying to make
it hard for you.
They're not trying to make you jump through hoops for the sake of jumping through hoops.
But let's say that you get like 20,000 applications.
So recently we were looking for a summer intern and there's just loads, loads of applications that
come in.
And, you know, as much as you really want to give each application all of your attention and just.
You know, really understand each person.
You don't really have the time.
So you're going to have to think about ways of making it a bit easier on yourself.
Right?
So one of those ways is by looking at somebody's qualification.
But another way, and probably something that I'm more fond of is actually just looking at what are
they capable of doing?
And this really is a key.
So.
You need to build a portfolio.
You need to show the world, not tell the world what you can do.
So create some web apps.
If you want to become a web developer, create some iOS apps if you want to become an iOS developer.
And don't just.
Don't just stick to the the stuff that you see in tutorials.
You have to somehow stand out.
And one of the best tips I can give you is, again, think from the recruiter's point of view.
They want to hire a web developer.
They are probably a manager, right, of some sort.
What are the kind of tools that they use every day?
So if you're a manager, especially if you're a product manager or a software lead, you're probably
going to use some form of task management like Trello or Asana.
You're probably going to use GitHub or something like it.
Hub like Bitbucket.
Think about the tools they use and build a tool that they can understand.
So if they use Trello or Asana, I'm sure there's pain points.
I'm sure there are certain features that would be really cool.
So if you build a Trello clone, but you add in some features of your own, some something that you
think of that you think would be really useful, and then you show that manager what you've built.
They will instantly understand what you've built.
They will see the advantages of your product, and they will be able to attest to your skill, which
is what is so, so important.
So my advice, whenever you want to achieve any sort of goal that involves other people, is to think
from the other person's point of view.
All right.
So we've done a couple of questions from the ask page now, and I'm seeing so much chat activity.
I really want to get to know you guys a little bit better.
So I want to do a poll.
So it's going to be pull time.
All right.
So if you go ahead and take a look at my slide, I want to know where you are.
So where are you streaming from?
Now, what you need to do is to head over to this link.
So wait a minute, I'm going to remove this banner and you can see if you go to London, Apple.com forward
slash where it will redirect you to this horribly long URL that's underneath, which is a poll.
So choose an answer and I want to know what your location is.
All right.
So I think some of you guys have voted.
Let's see the results.
Okay.
I think there's like 200 votes now.
I'm going to take a look at the results.
All right.
So it seems like most people are from Asia.
Next is Europe and next is North America.
I mean, that kind of makes sense to me.
I think it's about evening time in Asia now and then in Europe where I'm at in London, we're kind of
during the day and then North America is just waking up.
So that's pretty cool.
All right.
So let's take some questions from YouTube.
You guys have been chatting away in there and I'm trying to look at it for.
Just to see what's actually happening if you're getting the audio and everything.
But let's take some questions from YouTube.
So go ahead and ask away.
All right.
So we got one here from Claudia, and it's going to cut off because it's quite long, but I'll read
it out to you.
I want to ask you about the way you learn new coding skills.
How do you go about teaching yourself new skills?
What's your learning process?
Okay, cool.
So.
I think one of the most useful skills.
Like that I've ever picked up is learning.
I think if you can learn quite quickly, then it's going to help you in pretty much all sorts of ways.
So.
One of the ways that I do, one of the ways I sort of conceptualize it is I try to take the entire topic
and I break it down into, you know, what are all the parts that I need to learn?
Because when you take a textbook or when you take I don't know, let's say I mean, for example, at
the moment I'm trying to learn German, right?
If I just took a dictionary, it would take me years, years before I will learn it.
And I see sometimes people learning programming a bit like that, like they try to learn every single
method, every single function in a particular programming languages API or, you know, just, just
trying to learn it.
All right.
And there's a lot of courses are also kind of like a reference guide kind of style where they show you
everything.
And I think in terms of learning, it doesn't really work.
Instead, what you kind of need to do is, again, you have to have a goal, right?
So if you're learning to program, maybe that goal is you have a particular app you want to build now
the certain foundational skills that you need.
But once you get past the foundation, then you're kind of doing like learning Lego.
You're trying to figure out, Okay, I need to learn this bit.
Where should I go for that?
I need to learn that part in order to do this.
So, for example, the way that I'm thinking about German, like learning German, I've realized I don't
need to write German.
I probably could read, but it doesn't really bother me.
All I want to focus on is actually listening and speaking, so that already makes my task a lot easier.
Now next, if I want to be able to speak well, then I have to practice, right?
So there's a really good course actually by Pimsleur that I use where all they do is they just teach
you a couple of ways of saying a sentence and then they get you to practice.
You just, you know, they'll be like, what is how do you say, I want to go to the restaurant?
How do you say I'm going to the restaurant?
How do you say I went to the restaurant, etc.?
And you have a lot of practice just putting the words together in some sort of logical way.
And then because it's not really interactive, it's just, you know, a list of sentences, I have to
say.
Then I will take that and take Google Translate, which can listen live to what you're speaking in German,
and I'll translate it to English text so then I can judge based on that translation.
Well, how good is my German?
Did I manage to conjugate my verbs correctly?
Did I manage to put everything together?
And then in terms of listening, one of the hacks that I kind of came up with, I guess, I'm sure it's
not original, but I watched a lot of shows on Netflix, as I'm sure a lot of you guys do.
But I discovered that if you listen to a TV show that's produced in another language, so for me it's
German.
You can switch on not only the subtitles, which is helpful, but you can switch on something called
audio described, which basically will describe to you it's intended for people who are unable to see,
to be able to hear what's happening in the show.
But to somebody who's also, you know, not really very good at the language hearing what's happening
on the screen being described to me in German, you know, it will be something like a man walks into
the room, the man takes the keys from the table.
Like, I can see that.
I can see what's happening and I can match up what's happening with what's being described.
And this has been really, really helpful for me to learn listening.
So yeah, basically what I would say is break down the problem, figure out the goal, just take the
parts that you need to do to achieve the goal and then see how you can practice those skills repeatedly.
That's that's probably the best way of learning.
All right.
Let's take another question from YouTube.
We got one from.
I think your name is Yuvraj Agarkar car, so it's going to cut off the text again, but I'll read it
out.
I'm 17 and I've completed your iOS and Web dev courses.
My question is how to be good at reading docs and also how to start a startup.
Okay, cool.
So there's two questions in there.
First question is how do you get good at reading docs?
The answer is it depends.
So firstly, there's a difference in the quality of documentation.
So I worked a lot with iOS, and so I'm mostly reading Apple documentation, which is I mean, it's
beautiful.
Like they've laid out the website really nicely, but if you've taken my eyes courses, you know that
I think they're kind of minimalist.
They're kind of just like, Oh yeah, we have this thing which you can use, but why don't you go and
like find out yourself how to do it?
So yeah, it's useful.
But you know, if you've ever looked at some of Google's documentation, especially flutter documentation
is absolutely incredible and.
You know, really like kudos to the team because it is the best documentation I have ever seen.
It's kind of like this is a method that we have in this particular module.
This is how you would use it.
Here's a code example.
Here are the various parameters that you can tweak, and it is just so good that you can sort of imagine
yourself being able to pick up how to use it very easily.
Whereas Apple kind of like, Yeah, we don't really care.
You know, if you make it, you make it.
If you make an app, there's enough people who make apps.
I don't know.
What is that?
They're thinking behind that documentation.
But it's it's very hard.
The second thing I would say is that you don't necessarily learn a lot from documentation.
It's kind of like if you were learning a language and your starting point was the dictionary, you'll
be there for a while.
So the good thing is that, you know, this kind of comes back to how you learn, right?
A lot of people still learn in a pre-computer, pre-internet kind of way where you read a book, you
your lecturer gives you a lecture.
You take notes, you memorize those notes, you read the book, you take more notes.
You do a test.
This, I would say.
Is good for exams or for school.
It's probably still the way you have to do it.
But if you actually just trying to learn a skill for life or for, you know, changing jobs or just
for yourself, it's not the best way because information is really cheap.
You can get hold of pretty much any knowledge or information you want just by typing it into Google.
So why should I store all of that information in my brain when you know it's just two or three keystrokes
away?
So I don't really like to do that.
And this comes back to documentation.
I don't remember documentation.
I don't learn documentation.
There are loads of methods that I'm not, you know, I don't remember how to use.
But the thing I know is that I have the skills to be able to understand the code when I need to.
So when I want to look something up, I look it up in the documentation.
Actually, usually I look it up in StackOverflow.
I try to see an example where it's used and then in the example I'll see a particular method that's
in the documentation.
And then if I want more background, I'll read up on it.
In the documentation it's much better to learn things as and when you need to.
So that's pretty much what I do.
So the next question is how to start a startup.
That's like a really big question.
And I think back in the ask, there's also somebody who asked, I think it was somebody called Oliver
who said, What do you recommend to aspiring entrepreneurs?
So I'm going to answer these two together.
So.
When I started.
So I kind of started building a startup while I was still working as a doctor, which is probably a
little bit masochistic because I was working these crazy hours like, Oh man, it was probably like
some 14 hour occasionally, like 16 hour days.
And but the good thing about medicine, at least, is you have night shifts or the good thing or the
bad thing and the night shifts, you know, to be humane, at least in Europe, after three days of
night shifts, we tend to get three days off.
So the first day you'll be completely destroyed, you'll be hardly human because you're trying to switch
time zones, right?
It's kind of like flying to Australia and back every week.
So the first day is kind of like gone, but the second and third days I found that I was able to kind
of recuperate those days and I would just go to the library and I would work on my startup.
So the first thing is you got to find time.
There is no perfect time to start a startup.
There is no perfect opportunity.
That's just going to hit you on the head.
Everything that we've built, everything every opportunity that's come to us has taken a lot of work
to prepare to get to that point.
Right.
I think there was this this thing that my granddad drilled into me, which is my late granddad.
He he used to take me to school on his bicycle every day.
And on this little, like 30 minute bicycle ride, he would give me these, like, um, chicken soup
style, like pieces of, like, nuggets of advice.
I was like so many pieces of advice, including, like, they're going to sound weird.
It's like, if you ate beans uncooked twice and you still continue eating uncooked beans, then that's
not very smart.
So I think what he's trying to say is, don't make the same mistake twice.
I don't know why it has to do with uncooked beans.
But another thing that he told me is that, you know, opportunities come to those who are prepared.
I'm pretty sure it was another food analogy because I do really well with food analogies.
That's the way I understand the world.
But he says that, you know.
Every time you see somebody looking like as if they were just an overnight success, it's never overnight.
You don't see all the hours and days that they've poured into doing something fruitful or not successful
or not until they get to the point where they're prepared enough to be hit by that opportunity.
So a good example, I think is, for example, we built the flutter course because.
Tim, who heads up the Flutter team at Google, took my iOS course and he loved it so much that he reached
out to me over Twitter and this is how we partnered with the Flutter team at Google to build this course
together.
Now, if I had just started building courses day one and, you know, firstly nobody would know about
you.
Secondly, you know, there's no track record.
And thirdly, I'm not even sure I would be able to build such a good course from scratch.
So.
You know, the idea is to spend all of your time preparing, your start up, working on it, and then,
you know, there will be moments, there will be wins and there'll be losses and you have to grab onto
the wins and not think too much about the losses.
That's pretty much in a nutshell how I think about.
Our startup.
Okay.
So I'm going to go back to the chat and I'm going to ask you guys for some more questions and let's
see if we got some good ones.
All right.
So I think when I was looking at the questions that people had asked previously and also in YouTube
right now, the one that I'm seeing a lot is this one.
It seems like everybody wants to know when the iOS 14 update is coming for iOS, or is there going to
be a new course?
When is it going to happen?
What is happening on that?
Should I wait for the course?
Should I continue the iOS 13 course?
What's happening?
Okay, so here's what is happening.
We've reviewed Big Sur and also the latest version of Xcode.
We're in the process of testing the course through all of these new pieces of software, and what we
realized is that the changes are not that great.
So there's basically not enough changes to.
They tweaked the style of Xcode a little bit and they've added some handy features, which we might
point out.
But essentially over, you know, what we've been doing is we've, we've been just sort of trying to
figure out how we can update the last parts of the course because they're more outdated.
Whereas the beginning modules sort of up to flash chat, I think.
So the first 14 or 15 modules we're going to keep as is because they still work, but we'll update some
of the interfaces.
So at least initially it won't be so confusing, but that means that there will be no new iOS course.
You won't have to buy anything or the updates that we're making through this winter.
Next spring will get added to the existing iOS course.
So don't buy any more courses.
Just keep the one that you already have and you'll see the updates roll in.
But if you're already learning with the course, don't worry, the changes are not that big.
You'll be able to you'll be able to figure it out.
So that's that's what's happening on that.
And let's see what other questions we've got in YouTube.
All right.
So we've got a question from Atharva Vasco and also some people on YouTube, it seems.
Do you watch anime?
Okay.
So that's.
Kind of.
It's interesting.
That's that's a question that everybody wants to know.
I wonder if it's because of all the memes I've put into the courses from anime.
So I.
I don't think that.
So the anime that I like basically is quite old school.
You know, your girl's not young.
And so, for example, Ghibli movies Spirited Away, it's like one of my favorite all time movies.
It I love it so much, but pretty much any Djibouti movie, it's it's amazing.
It's just like paints the scene.
But more recently, I'm kind of late to the bandwagon here, but Netflix started showing this sort of
a Western anime called Avatar The Last Airbender.
So if you haven't watched this, don't be put off by the name.
It has a horrible name, but it is so good.
It it's like reliving childhood, you know, like, if you could just go back to being a little child,
that's how it feels.
It's so wholesome and oh, my God, it's just so good.
If you haven't watch it, I wouldn't ruin it for you.
But it is literally the best animated show I have ever watched, and it has a special place in my heart.
Okay, what other questions have we got?
We've got a question from a 13 year old boy.
I think I've had hoots about hoots about dudes.
I'm not sure.
And he asked, What careers can I have at age 13?
Okay, so the full question I will read out because it's a little bit long.
He says that I'm a 13 year old boy.
I'm doing your web development course.
I'm even doing a course based on how to create A.I. and ethical hacking.
What careers can I have at this age or job that doesn't consider my age?
Please take this question.
Love the way you teach.
Found it easy to understand Avatar.
Okay, so firstly, why are you thinking about work?
You're 13 men.
Like, just enjoy life.
It's so good to be that age.
But then again, I have to say, like when I was when I was 13, I was probably the same as you.
I was also thinking about, like, how to get a job.
I don't know what it is.
I think you're probably an overachiever, like a type a person like me as well.
So.
When I was 13, I was thinking that I'd really like to have some pocket money because my parents didn't
really believe in pocket money and there were like sweets and snacks that my friends were having and
I was kind of jealous.
So I was like, You know what?
I'm going to make my own money.
So I decided to take an inventory of What am I good at?
And I tried out a couple of things.
One is I got legs I can walk.
So I signed up for this thing in the UK.
I'm not even sure what it's called and elsewhere, but basically there's this giant book, like a telephone
directory that we used to have, like pre-internet days.
It's called like the Yellow Pages in the UK, and you can basically go door to door lugging these like
two kilogram books and you get paid a pound.
So like about $1.20 for every one of these books that you deliver.
So the thing is that there's so heavy that like, I don't know that they're like two kilos each.
So if you imagine in ten of them and I was 13, that was pretty hard and I got some pocket money, but
I thought about iterating on that.
So, you know, coming back to startups, you've got to try something, you test it out, see if it
works, if people like it.
So if it gets you to your goal and if not you iterate.
So my iteration basically ended up in me thinking about what else do I have?
And maybe like manual labor isn't really my strong point.
So I thought that, well, you know, I'm like pretty good at maths, I'm pretty good at physics and
there's probably other kids who want to learn maths and physics.
So I printed out these little flyers like from my little home printer.
So like they were like this big each per add because I didn't want to waste too much ink.
And I cut it out of the page and it's about like eight ads per page.
And I went door to door around sort of my neighbourhood area, like an area that I thought was like
within walking distance.
And I posted it to everybody in the mailbox and then like some people actually called me up and then
I became a tutor, although probably illegally, because I'm pretty sure you're not allowed to work
and earn money at age 13 unless you're like supervised or something.
But that was like my first entrepreneurial bent.
So coming back to your question, what careers can you have at age 13?
Well, now that you have the Internet effectively, you could do anything you could like probably sign
up on Fiverr and start doing freelance gigs.
I think when people sign up to these freelance gigs, they always want to like charge what it's worth.
And I would say, just don't do that, don't, don't like go overboard charge way, way below what you
think it should cost.
So you want to build somebody a website, charge $5 for it, you know, and what you want to do is like
build up your reputation so as you get more clients and if they like what you do, hopefully you're
doing a good job because you know, you're my student, right?
So you're going to be pretty good.
And when you give the project back to them, you're learning like skills, like communication, how
to work with clients, what clients mean when they're saying like, Oh, I would like that to look more
classy.
What does that actually mean to a web developer?
Well, you're going to work that out.
So once you've got a good client, then you've got a word of mouth.
You've also got reviews.
You've got a client who can be your referee and you build up on that.
So you take on more clients, maybe you've got too much work.
So now you raise your you raise your price now $10, and then you've got like too much work again.
You raise your price to $20.
And that way eventually you'll get to the point where you're making enough pocket money to buy sweets
or whatever it is you know, you want to achieve.
Maybe you want to like buy stocks at age 13, maybe you're going to buy into Tesla.
I don't know.
But yeah, so that's that's my advice.
Let's see if we got some more questions on YouTube.
So.
Let's see what you guys are saying in here.
Oh, this is a really good one.
So this is a question from Dionysius.
Dionysius.
I think that's how you pronounce it.
And he asked, Understanding syntax is not so difficult.
Formulating syntax together with logic to build functional code is difficult.
What are the best strategies to connect the dots to build real world projects?
This is something that you guys upvoted a lot and it's something that we think is really important because
one of the sort of feedback that we always getting from students is, Yeah, okay, so like, you know,
I've completed this tutorial, I've completed that tutorial, but you know, after I'm done, I still
don't know how to make my project.
I still don't know like how to, how to build something, right?
So this was really like our thinking when we started building the 100 Days of Code Project.
I wanted to make a course basically, which starts out with tutorials and a lot of heavy sort of guidance.
But then to progress on to be able to let you experience what it's like when the training wheels are
off.
So when I first learned how to ride a bicycle, I was riding it and I didn't really have one of those
fancy bicycles with the training wheels.
I just had my dad, like, holding the bicycle from behind.
And, you know, initially I was just riding.
He was running behind.
And at some point he kind of let go.
And I didn't really notice and I could just start cycling myself.
But then when I turned around and I saw that there was nobody there, I immediately crashed.
Right.
So, yeah, I guess my, my track record with bicycles is not great.
But so I guess the learning point there is that, you know.
You can't always be in territorial land if you want to become somebody who's not dependent on tutorials.
So a lot of people have been asking me, hey, you know, this course hundred days of code, why is
it that there's like less and less video towards the end?
Is it because you haven't finished it?
What's happening?
So the answer to that is, no, it's not because I haven't finished it.
It's because it's really carefully thought out, believe it or not.
And the idea is to.
Be that person holding the bicycle from behind and then to eventually let you go, because I want you
to be able to finish that course and to get a job or to build your own start up, build your own project.
But that requires quite a bit of struggle.
And the struggle comes from building projects.
Right.
But, you know, when I say to people, the best way to learn to code after you finish your tutorial
is to build a project.
Will they say, I don't know, which project do I build and how do I build it?
I don't know how to get there.
So that's why we built this course, to try and make it so that initially you have sort of more step
by step, like video lessons, and then you have step by step text lessons with more dependence on the
documentation and on the kind of real tools that a developer would use like Google and StackOverflow.
You need to struggle.
You need to find out the answers for yourself.
But, you know, there's walkthroughs and there's guidance.
And then eventually to get you to the very end where you're actually building your own projects for
your own portfolio, which contains 100% your own code, which you can copy, right?
You can sell, you can do whatever you want because it's your own.
And what we've done is just provided the project ideas for you, something that we think is really feasible
that you can definitely do if you've completed the entire first 80 days.
So that was what we tried to do.
And, you know, I think the best way to build real world projects is to start small.
So don't start off trying to build a car, build a skateboard instead.
And then once you've built the skateboard, maybe add a handle to it, turn it into a scooter, and
then maybe once you've done that, turn it into a motorcycle and then turn it into a car.
Don't just go out there and be like, I want to build Facebook plus Twitter plus, you know, whatever
enterprise software and I'm going to do it like after I complete this course.
Like, that's just you're setting yourself up to fail.
You have to start with something simple.
All right, so what kind of running?
A bit over?
I said we'd do 45 minutes, but we're kind of close to an hour now, so I'm just going to glance at
the YouTube chat and try to see what you guys are saying, like live.
Let's do some quick questions, swift UI or UI kit.
So if UI is getting a lot better.
But you know, when we did the Swift the Objective-C to Swift conversion, it took like years.
Still like loads of apps are built with Objective-C.
So Swift UI is not something that you can learn and get hired for right now.
It's really fun and I really enjoy playing with it, but.
I don't really think it's serious enough, like for my needs at the moment.
So we're probably going to build in more tutorials to the existing course.
So if you miss that, you don't have to buy a new course.
Your existing iOS 13 course will get updated, but it's going to be probably more swift UI, a little
bit less uikit and then we're going to keep tweaking that percentage until, you know, until like when
Apple fully transitions.
But I want to do it slowly because right now the kind of skills that's really important that's going
to get you hired is uikit.
Can you make your iOS course like 100 days challenge code?
I think we thought about making the 100 days of code challenge.
We thought about like, what's the perfect language for it?
Because Python is something that you can do, like a lot of different things with like web development
or data science or scripting or automation.
Swift is pretty much all about making apps, and it just doesn't really work that well with it.
I think it works better when you can actually build real projects, like big projects that you can show
off and you can use.
I think it's just a better format.
Like none of the things that we do is random.
Like I spend a lot of time thinking about it.
Okay.
What kind of games do you prefer?
Computer slash android.
Oh, man.
I recently got into this steam game called Salt and Sanctuary.
It's a two player couch co-op, and it's just so good.
It's like it's got, like, the RPG elements, it's got platforming, it's got some combat, and it's
got, like, just a lot of elements.
It's like, really well-rounded.
And I discovered that it was actually made by like, one guy, essentially, he built the entire video
game, which is crazy.
It's a really good one.
And on Android, on phone.
Yeah, among us, it's a bit of a guilty pleasure if you haven't played it.
Don't don't start.
Okay, so what else are we seeing in the chat?
Will you intend to build a Java course?
Probably not.
I don't really like Java that much.
I feel like Oracle is going to like send me a lawsuit just for saying the word Java.
So the funny story is that we obviously have like an Android course and Android courses built with Java.
So we thought it'd be a good idea to put the Java logo on the course image.
And then we got this like really serious letter from Oracle saying, Yeah, you're going to take off
our logo because you don't own the logo for Java.
And we were like, Hey, man, we're trying to teach your technology to people.
Like, we're trying to teach more people Java, which you own, but they were like, Nope.
So yeah, I think they're bit they're a bit old on that front.
Let's see, what other messages have you guys got?
I'm completing 100 days of code course with my grandfather.
Wow.
That's amazing.
I've heard of people completing it with, like, their kids, like the ten year old or 11 year old kids.
But that's pretty awesome.
You know, this is another good point.
My friend was recently telling me the story that they so he works at a bank and he was saying how they
have this guy who is like the godfather of like their platform's code and nobody else can like fix it
other than him.
And I was like really curious, you know?
And so one day the like, grandmaster of the finance company's code comes in and he's got like a walking
stick.
He's like 69 or something, and he's like really old.
He's got like white heads.
And it turns out that their entire system is built on pretty much like, you know, like really, really
old tech, right?
And this is like the only guy who really understands how to do it, these kind of old programming languages
like COBOL or Fortran, you know, because there's not actually a lot of people who know it and it's
super hard.
Like if you tried learning.
C And you think that's hard like try learning Fortran, it's it's even harder.
I guess there's also a machine code, but you know, there's also a point to be made that maybe somebody
should teach like these old languages because there's obviously some future in it as well.
Like all of the airline industry banking, they're all built on COBOL, which is crazy.
What are the best books that you've read this year?
The best books.
Oh, there's a really good book on negotiation by Chris Voss, and he's like this ex FBI negotiator,
so like negotiating hostage releases and everything.
And he wrote this book called Oh, man, what's it called?
Something about like.
Never split the difference.
That's it.
So he basically just teaches you like how to negotiate, like if you want to buy a used car, how to
get the best deal.
But using all of these skills that he got from like the FBI, which is absolutely insane.
It was a really good book.
Okay, so what else have we got?
Java, C++, or Python, which is the most powerful.
I mean, what?
What are you trying to like?
You like street fighters.
You know how on YouTube there's all these, like, videos of, like, bear?
This is Cobra.
I think somebody should make a YouTube video where it's like Java programmer versus Python program.
I don't know.
I don't think any of them are more powerful.
I think they have their own uses.
It's like kind of saying, you know, hammer versus sor who's going to win.
Doesn't really make too much sense.
What have we got?
Web development or software development, which one do you prefer?
Ooh, that's a really hard one.
I like.
I like both, actually.
I don't know.
I don't have a strong feeling towards it.
I mean, okay.
So he's a bit of a a secret.
I don't really like JavaScript that much.
I think if you're somebody who's played with a lot of the newer languages that have been like developed
recently rather than a language that's all that's just had new things bolted on, like JavaScript.
You realize like how nice it is.
Like Swift is lovely, Kotlin is nice.
Dart like they're all really nice languages, python but JavaScript but web development you can do with
Python with JavaScript.
That's really your choice these days with so many frameworks.
What else have we got?
Can you say something about UI UX designing?
UI UX designing.
It's really important.
Oh, this is a good tip.
Don't think about you on UX at the end.
A friend of mine is a UX designer and she's really, really good.
But like she says, always what happens is like, companies will bring her in at the very end.
They're like, Oh, to sprinkle you like UX magic dust.
And it's like, No, that doesn't work.
You have to start from the very beginning.
So super important.
Like read more about it.
Try out loads of apps.
I know that these days people kind of like just have seven apps on their phone and they don't really
add any other ones.
But try out apps, try out that user experience, and then just make a note of the ones that you really
like.
Like recently in the UK, there's a bank startup called Monzo, and when you get their bank card in
the mail, when you're setting it up.
So when you're doing that with like a normal bank, like HSBC or whatever, you have to like call up
the customer service.
You have to go into the branch, they type some stuff, you fill in some forms.
This Monzo card came in.
I had to download the Monzo app and then it was literally like using NFC touch to a phone, and then
it was like, it's all set up.
That was amazing.
That is good UX.
That is some fantastic us.
Last question I'm going to take I'm going to pick the last question before we take off.
Let's see,
what's the last question?
Oh, so hard.
La la, la.
Okay.
I'm going to pick you because I see you in the Q&A doing 100 days of Python all the time.
Matea, you're like really, really strong on the motivation.
So your question is, how do you make prices for software?
Like how do you price software?
I think is what you mean.
I mean, theoretically, what people say is price your software at the price that people are willing
to pay for it.
But I mean, I'm not really the right person to ask because I don't really like doing marketing or really
like doing sales.
I just don't like when I make my courses.
I kind of think if it's something that people want, then they'll get it.
Like, I don't want to like.
I don't want to, like, tell people to buy something that they don't need or they don't want.
You know, like I think the marketing team wanted me to do this AMA so that we could promote the new
100 days of Python course.
But they're going to hate me because I haven't done any of that, and I'm not planning to.
Yeah, I mean, check it out.
It's in the description below.
If you want to get the 100 days of Python course, you can get it for whatever price is there.
But.
You know, I think you should price your product depending on its appeal.
So if it's something that has mass appeal, then, you know, you can afford to make it a bit cheaper
if it's something that has only very few people interested in it.
Like, for example, if tomorrow I wanted to build a software for people who are livestreaming on YouTube
so that they can play music as a DJ.
Like I don't know how many people are interested in it.
Maybe a lot actually.
I don't know.
But if it's something that's really niche, then you've got to price it more because you know, considering
the amount of time that it takes to develop.
But I mean, a good example is that our team thought really hard about how we price our courses.
And one of the things that we thought about is that.
You know, if we can afford to make it cheaper than we will, because, yes, people will buy it for
$200.
And yes, you know, six people worked on this project for almost two years.
And they, you know, they should bring out a product that's worth a lot.
But at the same time, you know, like a lot of people around the world have very different living conditions.
I know that I lived in Malawi for a while in Africa.
And, you know, I know like in villages and, you know, people don't have a lot.
So what you might think is a lot is what you might think is a little is actually a lot to some other
people.
So we really wanted to be able to make choices that anybody can afford.
So I would just say, you know, really depends depends on you.
So I think this is going to be the last question, unless there's something fun in here.
Can I work at Upper Income Day?
Well, I mean, there's COVID, but there's also like remote positions.
We're thinking of maybe hiring some interns at some point.
But I don't really know how it'll work.
Maybe we'll announce it as, like, an educational announcement.
I don't know, but we'll think about that.
All right.
So it's now way, way past time and my tummies kind of rumbling.
You know how it is.
The girl is hungry, so I'm going to probably sign off and.
So thanks, you guys.
All 1000 of you guys or more who joined in for the live stream today.
And I hope you will carry on coding and I hope you all the success in the world from your instructor,
Angela.
Good night.
Good morning.
Wherever you are.
By.