Now, first things first.
In order to get started, we need to install the required tools and do some setup of those tools in
order to start development on the Internet computer.
Now, I've listed all of these steps together for you in a handy Google doc, and if you look inside
this current Udemy lesson, you'll see a link to this published on the internet so you can follow along
with me step by step.
There's a couple of things that you need to copy and paste, so I really recommend using it.
If you are a Windows user, then you can skip this video and head over to the next one where I've got
all the instructions specifically for Windows.
Now the first step you should already have done, which is to install Node.
We covered Node extensively in this course and in all likelihood you probably already have it installed.
But if you don't simply click on this link and head over to the website and download this one on the
left. It's really important that you download the LTS, which stands for long term support rather than
the one with the latest features, because the Internet computer will only work with the long term support.
Now, if you already have node installed, I recommend just doing a quick version check using node -
-version and hopefully it's 16 or above.
If not, again, go over here and just download the latest version.
Now the next thing you're going to need is a DFX.
So this is the way that we're going to be able to work with the entire computer locally to be able to
deploy our applications and to run our code.
So firstly, we're going to need to open up the terminal app, which you saw me open just now already.
If you don't know how to do that, simply head over to spotlight and search for terminal and open it
up.
Now we're going to copy this command wholesale as it is, and be careful that you don't drop any of
these double quotes at the end or anything.
Just select it in its entirety.
And then I want you to paste this as an entire line into your terminal and hit Enter.
Now, the installation process will take a little while, but once it's done and your DFX is successfully
installed, you'll be able to check and confirm this by writing dfx ---version and it should
give you a version of 0.9.3.
Now the final thing you need to do is to download the latest version of VSCode if you haven't already.
And this is a popular code editor, and we're choosing VSCode in this case because it has the tooling
to work with Motoko and to be able to develop for the Internet computer.
So just go ahead and download and install if you haven't already got it.
Now the final step in all of this setup is to install the Motoko VSCode extension.
And you can either do that by searching for it inside VSCode or simply heading over to this link that
I've got for you,
clicking install and it should take you straight through to VSCode
where you can install it.
Just make sure that if you are searching for the extension that you actually got the one that is called
Motoko from the Dfinity Foundation, because there's quite a few other ones that are named in a similar
fashion.
But there you have it.
You're now ready to build your very first Internet computer application.
Our, testing ground, our
Hello World App.
But the first thing we're going to do before we get started is to create a dedicated project folder.
So what I've got is something called ic-project, Internet computer projects, in my files.
And it's really handy to have this so that you can keep all the projects in the same place and keep
it nicely organized.
So I recommend going to your desktop, hitting the command button and hitting the up button in order
to get to your users of root folder.
And you can create the new folder ic-projects right here.
Now, once you've created your folder, I want you to go ahead and open up terminal and we're going
to navigate to that new folder by writing cd and then dragging that folder into the terminal and
hitting enter.
Now we're inside this project folder where we're going to run that command that you see here.
So I'm just going to copy it wholesale and then paste it into my terminal and hit enter.
Now it's going to go through the process of creating a new Internet computer project, which comes by
default with some sample code.
And it functions as a Hello World project.
Now you'll know it's done once you see the Dfinity logo and we're now going to open up this new project
inside VSCode.
So go ahead into VSCode and click on Open and then select that project folder inside the ic-projects
folder that you created and click open.
And now you should be able to see all of the code that was automatically created, including some Motoko
code and also some HTML and JavaScript.
So now we're going to try and deploy this project following the step by step instructions.
So go ahead and open up a new terminal and I want you to write dfx
start and this is going to start the local Internet computer.
And once you see something like info starting server listing on something, something, something,
then you're ready to go ahead and split out another terminal window by clicking on this button right
here. And inside this other terminal window, you're going to write dfx deploy in order to deploy this
new project onto the local Internet computer network.
Now that's going to take just a little while.
But once it's done, you can go ahead and run npm start to start your server. And if you scroll up,
it actually tells you where your project is running.
So you can copy this
URL and paste it into your browser in order to see your brand new intact computer dapp.
So you can enter your name here and click on the button and it should greet you by your name.
So super simple, but if you manage to get here and get this running, then that means all of the installation
and setup has been completed successfully and you are now ready to start writing some code.
So go ahead and skip the next lesson, which is installation set up for Windows users and head straight
on to begin making your very first Internet computer project.