Hey, guys.
In today's lesson, we're going to be talking about Express Middlewares, the man in the middle that
you're going to see in a lot of node and express based applications.
What exactly is a middleware?
Well, it kind of is something that just sits in between the raw requests that come in.
So when a request comes into the server and before it gets processed by all of the route handlers,
such as our GET, POST, PUT, the functions that we've planned for how to deal with a particular request, there
is something in between, namely the Middleware that can work with these requests before they get processed
and reach their final destinations.
Now, what kind of things can middleware do?
Well, one option is to pre-process the requests.
So when we know that a request is going to go to multiple handlers, maybe it could be processed by
GET, POST or PUT requests,
t his intermediate stage where we have our middleware can actually go ahead and change aspects of the
request or perform various functions on that request before it goes to its final routing.
Also, we can use middleware for Logging the requests.
So how long does it take the request to come through?
What type of request GET, PUT, POST, etcetera?
What is the status of the request being handled?
We can also use middleware for Authentication.
So before we let the request through to our back-end handlers, we can see if that request is actually
came from a client that is authorized to make that request, say, if somebody wants to go and change
Facebook's databases to call it Handbook instead of Facebook, we have to make sure that that request
is allowed by that user.
And then finally, we can also process any errors in the requests.
We can identify them and handle those errors before they go through to the handlers as well.
So a number of functions can be performed basically before we allow the request through. A really commonly
used middleware in Node and Express
back-end engineering is something called Body Parser.
Body Parser is, as it says, a body parsing middleware.
What does that mean?
Well, it can look at the request bodies before your handlers actually access them.
This basically gives our request a new property called the body property.
And very commonly this is used to handle form data.
When you create a HTML form, such as when you have a login form and you want the user to put in their username
and password, when you press that login button in order to get access to the data that was inputted
in there, you might use something like body-parser to parse the body of that POST request.
Here's a real life example using code.
This is what a HTML form element looks like.
It starts with a form tag, closes with a form tag, and the properties that you usually see are "action",
which in most cases will refer to the route that you want your server to handle this request.
And also you'll have a "method" which usually will describe how you want this data to be processed in
your back-end.
Is this a form for updating information on your server, or posting information, or deleting information?
It could be a number of things,
basically. The other parts of the form that you normally see is the "label" and "input" elements.
The label is simply the place where we label the next input because an input is usually just a box.
It doesn't really tell the user what you expect to go in there.
So normally it's a pair where you have a label element followed by an input element.
Now the input element usually has two properties that you'll see, "type",
so what kind of input is this?
And you can have things such as radio buttons, you can have things such as checkbox input, you can
have a dropdown list inputs,
but the most common one and the simplest is just a text field.
And then we have something called "name", which is going to label the data that goes into this input.
So if I put in something like my email, blah blah blah@blah blah blah, then that piece of data
will have a key
associated.
So a key / value pair.
And the key will be whatever it is you assign the name property to be.
We can also add the "required" attribute, which means that this input cannot be submitted until there
is a piece of data that's added into it.
And finally, we have a type of input that is a "submit" type, which actually is a button, and you can
tell what the button should say.
It could say, okay, it could say submit in this case, but whatever it is you want the button to say,
you would add it to the "value" attribute.
If this HTML was displayed in a browser, then this is what you would see.
This part is the first label in this form.
This part is the first text input.
This is the next label, and this is the next input.
These are all text inputs and they will expect a value in there.
And then finally we have our submit button, which is also an input, but it has the value of submit,
which is what we assigned over here.
So HTML forms are pretty simple and you'll get used to this format pretty soon.
But the important thing is how do we incorporate this form into our backend?
So I want you to go ahead and download the exercise 3.4 Middleware.zip from this current lesson,
so in the course resources for this lesson. And then once you've downloaded and extracted it, you
will see that it has a bunch of files already in there.
As always, the first thing we're going to do is to cd over into this new folder and then run npm install
so that everything that's inside the package.json or the dependencies gets installed.
Now notice the difference in this particular project.
I've actually got a public folder and the public folder usually is the place where we put our static
files such as our HTML files, CSS files, images, things that don't really change and don't need to
be acted upon.
What we're going to do is we're going to try and render this index.html as the thing that we're going
to return from our server.
Previously, you've seen res.send, but in this case, I'm actually using a different express method which
is called res.sendFile.
Now res.sendFile requires an exact path in order to know which file to send back.
Now of course, the file that we want to send back over to the client is our index.html.
In order to get the full path of that particular file, we need to do a little bit more.
When your server is hosted on a cloud computer, when it's no longer locally hosted, as is the case
for most servers, then in order to figure out this directory name where the file lives in, it takes
a little bit of work.
And these are the lines of code that are required for this.
So firstly, we're going to import something called dirname directory name from the "path" module that's
bundled with Node, and then we're going to do a little bit of conversion in order to eventually end
up with this constant called directory name, which basically is all of the path up until the path that
we want to access.
In my case, it could be my Mac, and then it would be my username, and then it would be the Web Development
folder and so on and so forth.
And it's going to be able to figure all of that out just by using these three lines of code.
And this also means that you don't have to type out the exact path, right?
Because when it is true for local development, such as the path at the moment, once we've actually
put our server up into the cloud and host it somewhere, then that's no longer going to be the file
path.
So we need to figure it out dynamically and this is probably one of the best ways to do it using Node
and Express. If I go ahead and console log this,
directory name, plus the location of my file,
you'll see that if we go ahead and use nodemon and then run index1.js,
you can see that if I hit up the GET route, so I'm just going to use Postman to do that, to hit up localhost:
3000.
You can see it's going into
Users/angelayu/ Web Development Projects, but this entire directory path was generated using these three lines of code and
your path will of course be different depending on whether if you're on Windows or Linux or Mac.
And once your project is hosted somewhere online, then that will be relative to the computer that it's
hosted on.
Now that we've seen that, let's go ahead and delete this and let's test this out to see if we can actually
see that index.html page being sent over when we make a GET request to the home page. In order to do
that, let's make sure first that our server is up and running, which it is, "Listening on port 3000".
And then let's go ahead to our localhost:3000 and you can see that this HTML page is coming from over
here,
h1 Band Name Generator.
There's a form with a label for street name, a label for pet name,
and this is basically the exercise that we're going to compete by the end of this lesson.
But you can see that in this case, I'm not just sending over a little bit of HTML when I do the res.send,
instead, I'm sending over an entire file that I've linked to.
So now that we've figured out the first part, let's go ahead into the main topic of today's lesson,
which is how to use middleware, right?
And the middleware that I want you to use, which is something that you will use again and again and
again, is called Body Parser.
We're going to go ahead and install body-parser and then we're going to use body-parser in order to
parse the information that's coming in through the form on our website.
So remember, this is our index.html page and when this "submit" button is pressed, what's going to happen
is that form is going to make that POST request to the path that we specified, which is
/submit.
So what we need to do is to have a route handler that is able to handle a POST request to that particular
path.
And then we're going to use body-parser, which we're going to install very soon, and then we're going
to use it as a piece of middleware in order to parse the information that comes in from the form.
So from this HTML form.
And then we're going to add that data to the request object so that we can actually console log it under
req.body.
This is the goal and this is the code that's required to do it.
If you look inside the index1.js file, that is basically our starting point for adding this
body-parser middleware.
I want you to go ahead and use the code that you see here.
So pause this video at this point and I want you to implement this code so that it actually works live
on your end.
So you should be able to go to localhost and type something into the street and pet fields and hit submit
and then see what you typed into the form in your console log.
Pause the video and give this a go.
All right, so let's run through this together.
So firstly, making sure that we're inside index1.js because there are many sub-parts to this
coding exercise
in this lesson. We're going to go ahead and stop our server to npm install the body-parser module.
Now this is just so that you know where that body-parser comes from because of course if you look inside
the package.json, I've actually already got it set as a dependency, but when you're creating this
from scratch, you will need to install the body-parser module.
Once we've done that, let's go ahead and import body-parser into our index1.js. So now we can
use it and we're going to add this as a middleware by using the use method.
This method gets called before any of the route handlers.
Once we've got the use method, then we can add in our middleware function, which in our case is called
body-parser.
Now in order to use body-parser, we need to tell it what kind of data we want to parse.
And in our case, because we're dealing with a HTML form, we want to choose the URL encoded method.
Inside here,
there is one obligatory option that we have to set, which is this option called "extended", and you
can set that as true or you can set that as false,
and it basically just determines what is being used behind the scenes to parse the data that's coming
in.
And in pretty much 100% of the times, this is a line of code that you're going to write.
And once you've done that, then we get an extra power using this middleware in the sense that every
single request object now has a body.
Whereas before, without this, if you try to tap into req.body, you'll get undefined.
There's just nothing there.
But now with this body-parser parsing information coming in, we can in fact access it.
Now the place we want to access it is not going to be in the GET because the GET handler is just meant
to send back a resource that the user wants.
It's not meant to really deal with things coming in.
So instead we're going to create an app.post() method and we're going to hit up the route that the
form is going to send and act on, which is /submit.
So let's make sure that those two bits match in terms of capitalizing and also the whole spelling and
everything.
And then next we've got our request, response (req, res) and then our anonymous function, and we're going to go ahead
and console log the req.body object.
So now that we have req.body, we can send something to our server and see what information
we get.
So I'm going to use Nodemon and hit up our index1.js, and now we can go into Postman and go into
the localhost:3000/submit as our route. Making sure it's selected as POST and then under
this tab called body, this is where we can simulate a form.
So make sure the x-www-form-urlencoded option is selected because that's what we are handling.
And then go ahead and add in some pieces of data and you can add whichever key value pairs you want.
Once I go ahead and hit Send, you'll see that console log being enacted upon because we hit up the
POST route and I'm getting those key / value pairs being printed in here.
Now, if I go ahead and stop using body-parser as my middleware and I try that again, then you can
see that I'm getting undefined.
There is no body to my request.
So let's enable that once more.
And this time we're going to hit up the POST request from our HTML form here.
Our Band Name Generator is a very simple website that takes the street name that you grew up on, which
in my case was Aberdeen Road, and then your pet name, which in my case was a rabbit that I very creatively
called rabbit.
And then once I hit submit, it's actually going to make that request, which is the POST request to
the route that's /submit.
And when we take a look down here, you can see it has encoded this first part, which corresponds to
the name of that input.
And the second part is the value that was placed inside that input, which I wrote as "Aberdeen".
And it's the same for the next input as well.
That's the superpower that we managed to gain using the body-parser middleware.
In the next lesson, we'll learn to use another popular middleware package as well as learn how to write
our own custom middleware with Express.js.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.