All right.
So now that we've managed to add notes, be able to pull the notes out from Motoku backend, but
also we need to be able to delete them.
As I showed you earlier, you can delete them right now, but that's just on the frontend.
As soon as you hit refresh and we pull in all of our notes from the blockchain, it doesn't actually
change.
Let's fix that.
Notice here in our app.jsx, we've got the deleteNote function and all it does at the moment is
it updates our constant notes using the setNotes method to filter through all of the notes and check
for the one that has the index that's selected and then basically get rid of it from the previous notes.
That is why this frontend appears to work, but we need to link it up with our main.mo so that
when we actually hit refresh and we pull in these notes that it actually persists.
So let's go ahead and go into our main.mo and create this function.
So it's going to be a public function so that we can reach into it from a JavaScript,
and I'm just going to call it removeNote.
And in order to know which one to remove, I'm going to add an ID, which is going to be a natural number
because it's going to be zero or above.
And let me just add the semicolon so I get rid of this error here.
Now, in order to remove a particular item with a particular ID or index from the list that we've got
here, we actually have to do a little bit of a grunt work of our own because if you look through the
documentation as of right now, in 2022, there actually isn't a utility function for the list in Motoko
that allows us to just remove that index.
So we have to figure out how to do it using the available methods.
And to be honest, it took me quite a while to actually figure out how to do this, but I think I've
figured it out now.
So firstly, we've got a method here called take which returns the first n elements of a given list.
If the given list has less than n elements, then this function returns a copy of the full list.
So we supply two arguments.
One is the list that we want to take from, and the next is the first n elements.
So I've created this Motoko playground that you can find
if you look in the course resources. And if you head over to the URL in the course resources, you should
see something like this with the code that I've written here.
So I've got this variable called notes, which is a list of text elements, and then I add A, B, C,
D sequentially into this list.
Now remember that we said that push actually doesn't append, but it actually pre-pends.
So what do you think notes actually looks like?
Because we can test this.
If I go ahead and deploy, it's going to bring up a candid UI for me to work with.
And once that's done deploying, you can see we've got our three public methods here: drop,
getNotes and take. getNotes is going to show me what the current state of the notes is.
If I go ahead and click query, you can see that it shows us what the lists currently look like.
Now if we go ahead and click on UI, you can sort of see it a little bit better
how the structure of a list is different from an array, because when we add it using push, we start
out by adding A and then we add B and then we add C and then we add D.
It actually got added to the beginning, so pre-pended to our list. But also it doesn't look like a
list because they're not within the same hierarchical level.
In fact, it's almost like we've got an array that has many, many layers of embedding, and that's
why we had to convert it into an array before we send it over to our JavaScript so that we can actually
convert it out of this format and into a format that can be easily understood by the JavaScript.
This is the first aspect that's probably pretty weird that when we push items onto this list in the
order of ABCD, they actually go in in reverse order.
Now the next thing I want to show you is how this take function works.
So if I decided to take 2, what happens?
What do you think will be the new value of notes?
Because here I'm running take and I'm taking whatever I enter in candid here from the list of notes
and then I set the note to update it to the new list.
So if I go ahead and call this function and once that's done, then I click query, then you can see
what it's done is I've just taken the first two items from the list, which is D and C, remember,
they get added in in reverse order.
So our goal is to figure out some sort of way to implement a method, kind of like a remove at index.
So if we want to remove at index 2 basically in this case remove the B from this list, then how do
we actually use all of these methods that list provides to be able to do something like this?
Well, the first step is we're going to use that take.
So if we say take 2, what happens is we take the first two elements and we turn that into the list.
So we end up with D and C. Now next we can use this drop function which drops the first n elements
from the given list.
So in our case, if our list is the first argument, the second argument is how many elements to drop
from the list.
So let's try this again.
If we deploy and go ahead and click upgrade our canister, because our notes is not stable, it will just
be reset to the original.
And once that's done,
if we click query, you can see we've got our DCBA back.
So now if I go ahead and use the drop method and I say drop 2 and I call this method, then if I query
my getNotes again, you can see I'm left with B and A.
So how does this drop method work?
Well, if we say drop 2, it's basically going to take the first two elements and drop it from the
list.
So then we end up with whatever else remains, which is B and A.
So we've dropped the first two elements from the list.
Then to summarize, if we want to build this new method that doesn't exist, remove (index: 2) to
get rid of this B, then we have to combine our take 2, which takes the first two items, with our
drop where we drop 2.
Now that's going to end up giving us B and A.
So if we actually want to remove the item at index two, which is the B, then we have to drop the index
plus one in order to get A.
So then it will drop the first three items.
And through using a final method that we have on the list, which is called append, which allows us
to join essentially two lists together, we can join what was the result of the take (2) with the drop (2)
+ 1, and then we would end up with the result that we want D, C, A - B.
So we basically have to go through this slightly complicated process in order to be able to remove a
note from our list at the id which is the index that is passed in.
And I recommend, before you write the code to take a look at this playground. Just head over there,
deploy it, try out some different things and make sure you understand how drop and take actually works.
And then I want to set this to you as a challenge to write the function here so that when we get sent
over an id which could be 0, 1, 2, 3, basically the index of the item that needs to be
removed,
coming back to our slide here, if we wanted to remove B, then the index that you would get passed
is 2 because we start counting it 0.
So D is 0, C is 1, B is 2.
So when you get that 2, how do you actually remove that element at that index using those three methods
that we mentioned, which was take, drop and append?
Now, in addition to that, you'll also have to update the code in the app.js so that you actually
call that delete method and pass over that ID, which is going to be the index.
And if you manage to do all of that, then when you head back to the Keeper app, you should be able
to delete your notes and when you refresh they should not reappear.
So this is the challenge I'm sending you.
It's quite difficult.
Have a go, see if you can do it.
And then if you can't, or if you want to watch me walk you through it, then head back over here and
we'll do that.
Pause the video now.
All right.
So the first thing we said we're going to do is we're going to take our list, which is our notes,
and we're going to take the number of items that correspond to the ID that we want to remove.
To do that, we're going to use the List.take. Notice previously
every time we use the method from the list type, we've always had to use List.take and this List
.take expects two arguments:
one is the list you want to take from,
second is a natural number that corresponds to how many items you want to take from it,
so the n. Our list is notes and we want to take the index using this ID that we get passed.
Then I'm going to set it to equal a constant, which I'll call listFront because this will be the new
beginning of our list.
And then I'm going to create a listBack which is going to be created using list.drop.
So we're going to drop the list notes and we're going to drop the number that corresponds to the id
that we get plus one.
If this doesn't make sense to you, then just simply try it out.
Try it out using that playground and see what you actually get to be able to understand it.
But basically we're going through this three step process in order to remove an item when we're sent
the index of that item to remove.
The final step is we're going to reset our notes
so using that := sign, we're going to set it to the List.append and we're going to append
the listFront to the listBack.
And now through these three lines of code which you could if you want to simplify, but I think it's
easier to understand it when we split it out, then we achieve this remove at index functionality.
So we get sent the index and we use that index to update our notes to exclude that item by going through
this take and drop process.
And once we've done that, then we have to go back to our app.jsx and we're going to leave the
setNotes as it is because that's just going to handle the frontend and make things happen immediately.
But in addition, we're going to tap into our dkeeper and we're going to call that method that we created
just now, which is removeNote and we have to parse it
the value of the id that we get in this function.
Remember, that id comes from the index, which is indexed to correspond to the note that we want
to delete.
Finally, let's just cap that off and hit save and let's deploy our canister again.
Once that's done, let's head back over to our Keeper app.
Let's refresh.
And because we've redeployed our canister, our notes have been cleared.
So let's create our first note.
Add it.
Notice that it appears.
And then.
Now let's add another note.
And now I'm going to delete this first one so it immediately disappears.
And that is because of these lines of code.
But then if I refresh, notice how it doesn't reappear.
And that's because we're pulling it using the fetch data,
this removeNote at id has already removed the deleted note so that when we query for the list again,
then it doesn't show up in there.
And this way we've managed to implement the backend for our keeper to be able to add notes, to be
able to view them and have them persist, at least as long as we don't reset our backend.
And then to be able to delete them when we don't want them anymore and for that to persist as well.
Now, there's one final thing.
As you noticed, whenever I deploy or whenever I upgrade my canister, my notes get cleared.
And we can show that by updating something in the code.
Because remember, when you hit deploy and your code actually stays the same, it doesn't actually reset
the code.
So let's just go ahead and add a Debug.print to add a inconsequential line of code.
Now because this has updated the code of our main.mo,
if I go ahead and run dfx deploy, then it's actually going to force this code to upgrade our canister
which means this note's variable gets emptied out and gets to start from the beginning.
So now if I go back to my localhost, I hit refresh,
you'll notice that all the notes will disappear.
But we have one trick up our sleeve, and you've got it.
It's that stable keyword.
By turning this into a stable variable,
our list now persists across upgrades, which means that we've basically got a permanent storage solution
for our dkeeper app.
And now not only do we have a backend, because if I go ahead and hit deploy and I hit refresh, firstly
they don't disappear because we've got that storage on our backend.
But now if I go into my main.mo, I change the code significantly.
So delete that line for debug or add a line for debug,
basically either way forcing it to update my canister when I do dfx deploy.
So even though everything has now been upgraded and this code has now been refreshed, it doesn't matter
because if I go back once it's done and I hit refresh, all my notes are persisted.
It's as if I have a database in the backend, but I didn't really have to do anything other than add
that one stable keyword.
And that's something I think is super fantastic and really, really interesting.
It really means that we don't have to think so much about databases and getting things in and out.
And this is a really, really incredible way of writing code and creating applications.
So I hope you enjoyed building this to dkeeper app and taking the React frontend to combine it with
a internet computer blockchain-based backend and now being able to persist this.
So the main takeaways from this module was to show you how you can actually create apps writing
Motoko on the ICP blockchain, but also incorporate beautiful advanced frontend, whatever it is you
want to do on the frontend using React, thus being able to take our web3 applications really into the
future and to be able to make it look as beautiful as any web2 application while retaining the power
of an application that runs on the blockchain.
I hope that was fun
and I'll see you on the next module where we're going to be creating our own cryptocurrencies and our
own tokens on ICP.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.