Hey.
Well done for completing yet another module.
Man you're really getting these like modules like out of the way.
Now I want to share with you another tip of mine that has really helped me to be able to concentrate
better.
And the trick is to basically study or, when I'm working, work on something that's hard, that I've put
off,
when I'm in a fasted state, so that means the first thing when I wake up in the morning. I brush my teeth,
and I sit down, and I just do this difficult thing. And I find that, you know, when you have lunch, and especially
if you have something quite heavy, like in carbs, like a pizza or something, you feel your brain like going
to sleep, right? It's like really really hard to concentrate and everything just feels so, 'Oh, like I can't
wait to just go home.
I can't think.'. And I find that if you try to work when you're in like the opposite of that, when you've
just woken up, you haven't eaten anything yet, maybe you've had a black coffee but nothing that has any
sort of calorific value, right? In that moment,
I am like the sharpest as can be, and I found that, you know, through tweaking with my diet sometimes, like
especially like not having such a heavy lunch or not having so much carbs for lunch,
I find that I can think more clearly, but nothing beats that early morning and fasted, that early morning
fasted state,
and I'm just able to think more clearly. Now make sure, be safe, if you have diabetes or if you have
some other condition that like, that doesn't allow you to do this, then don't do it.
It's just a suggestion. It's just something that works for me.
So have a go at that and keep going.
You're getting really really far in the course now.