Hey, guys, now that we've learned about Clients, Servers and Databases, let's talk about which are
the technologies that professional developers use to create these backends.
So the programming languages used on the Front-end are pretty fixed.
It pretty much has to be HTML, CSS and JavaScript, because these are the only things that the browser
can work with.
And even though we've seen and worked with some frameworks on the frontend, and some common ones might
be React, Angular and Vue, these are all JavaScript frameworks and all that they do are they act as
the waiter who allows the client to interact with, ask questions about the menu, tell them that their
email is inputted in an invalid format,
do all of this front-end display and logic, and then when our request reaches the back-end, we can
actually work with pretty much any programming language.
Now these are some of the most popular ones Java, Ruby, PHP, C-sharp, Python and JavaScript.
And the reason why the backend language doesn't really matter is because as long as you're able to
use something to generate the HTML, CSS and JavaScript files to send back over to the frontend, then
it doesn't really matter what language you use to do that.
For example, if I wanted to Google the sunniest place on earth, I could do that in Japanese, German,
French, English,
it doesn't really matter what language I use, as long as at the end I get the results back in a format
that I can read.
Now, some of the most common backend frameworks that you might come across on the internet are Rails,
which is Ruby on Rails, The Java Spring Framework, the C-sharp, ASP.NET from Microsoft, PHP will be
using Laravel or Cake.
And then there's Python, which includes Flask and Django.
And then finally there's JavaScript, which has Node.
Now the framework and language that we're going to be using and learning on the back end is Node.js.
And reason number one is in the name.
It is a JavaScript back-end framework and we've invested so much time learning about JavaScript in order
to use it on the front-end with React, also with Vanilla JavaScript,
and now we want to be able to reuse that knowledge of JavaScript to work with it on the backend using
Node.js.
That's not the only reason though,
it's not just because we already know JavaScript
so we're using Node.
If you take a look at the latest StackOverflow Developer Survey, so they survey developers in this
case, 45,000 of them, and they classify them into Professional Developers and those who are Learning
to Code.
If we look at Professional Developers, the number one use of framework for developers is Node.js, and
this list mixes all of the frameworks, not just frontend or backend.
That's why you see React and Angular, and we're going to be covering the number one most popular framework.
So if you want to build a website and you want to be able to get access to the most helpful resources,
the most amount of documentation, the most amount of help online, then you're going to want to use
the most popular framework.
Also, if you want to get a job and you can see that the number one tool that professional developers
use is Node.js, that means that most of the jobs that are asking for a back-end developer or a
full-stack developer will expect you to know about Node.js
Now let's look at some of the other ones that I mentioned.
So ASP.NET, Django, Flask, that's Python, Laravel for PHP, Ruby on Rails,
these are all a lot less popular when you compare them with Node.js, and some of them don't really change
in their popularity.
There's always some work for people who are C-sharp developers.
There's always some work for people who work with Python, especially if you're working with a machine
learning web app.
Now, something like PHP, in the case of Laravel and Ruby, in the case of Ruby on Rails, I would
say are actually very much declining in popularity over the years.
And definitely, if you see a Web Bootcamp that's still teaching Ruby on Rails in this day and age,
you should probably think twice about signing up. And definitely, without a doubt, the most popular
backend framework that
you need to know is Node.js.
And because we can't make a 500 hour course, we have to focus on one technology instead of covering
all the technologies where you'll see me, you know, old and grey, and I'm still talking about one
of the other frameworks,
we have to make a choice.
And the choice that I've made is for ease of use because you already know JavaScript, but also the
most professionally important framework that you will be expected to know as a back-end developer,
which is going to be Node.js.
I hope you're excited to learn Node.js and we will start right away in the next lesson.