Hey you've completed another module.
Well done for that.
Now today I want to talk about the idea of having a routine and building a routine because when you
have a routine that's really helpful.
It means that you don't have to think so much about what do you have to do at each point of the
day.
So for example I have a morning routine, I actually have a daily routine which I try to stick to as much
as I can unless I'm traveling or I'm speaking or I'm teaching. So I tend to wake up around the same time about
7:30. And as soon as I wake up I jump out of bed,
I brush my teeth and I go for a walk.
Just getting some air into my brain.
For some reason I feel like just like I suffocate while I sleep or something, but moving along, getting the
blood flowing, getting some air into my lungs and then after like about a half an hour walk, I come back
and I try to do something difficult.
The first thing that I do during the day is usually something that I want to put off,
I don't really want to do
but it's something important, right?
It's not like you know like paying bills or taxes or something.
I mean those things do have to be done
but not like as important as building towards your goal or doing something that's going to further where
you are right now.
So I try to get that most disliked thing done first thing because once I've gotten that done then I have
this huge sense of achievement and if it's something that takes many days to do I'll try to get in at
least an hour of it.
So for you if you're learning to code and even putting off like a difficult module or difficult concept
or something you've been meaning to read up on but you just can't bring yourself to do it,
do that thing first thing in the morning.
And once you've gotten over that hurdle you'll feel so proud of yourself
having done like the hardest thing of the day.
Everything else you'll just be able to knock out
easier. So
have a try at that trick. And have a think about what you want your daily routine to be like.
See if you can structure your morning and your day so that you don't have to think about it, but it
just happens automatically.
Let me know what your routines are and what has helped you.
And I hope that this will also help you build up towards a habit of learning to code every day.