The very last thing we need to do in order to complete NFT Marketplace Project is to enable the buying
of the NFT assets.
Now, what's going to happen is we're going to need to take the amount that a NFT costs from the buyer's
wallet and transfer it to the original owner of the NFT and then finally transfer the ownership over
to the buyer.
And in order to do this, we're actually going to tie it back to the token canister that we created
earlier on so that we can start charging these DANG tokens and actually using them for something practical,
like buying and selling NFTs.
At the moment, all that happened when I click on the buy button is the 'Buy was triggered' is console
logged.
And by the way, if you don't have a NFT that is available to buy here, make sure that you use the
creating NFT for testing section
to simply mint an NFT that can be bought by this user on the frontend.
If we take a look at our item.jsx, we've got this function that we set out called handleBuy and at
the moment all it does is console.log
the 'Buy was triggered' text which is not very useful, but we're going to update it so that we can
actually make it do something.
Now, the first thing we need to do is to get our token canister up and running.
And hopefully you would have completed the module where we built the token canister and the frontend
for managing tokens.
But because I know that a lot of you might have not deployed that and also the code might be a little
bit different or a little bit messy,
I want us to be all working with the same token canister.
So in this current Udemy lesson, you should be able to download the token local compressed zip file.
And once you've uncompressed it, then you can go ahead and drag that folder into where you've got your
ic-projects.
Now once it's in here, then I want you to go ahead and open up a new window in VSCode and open up
that folder.
So mine's in my ic-projects and it's called TOKEN-LOCAL.
So now let's expand it so that we can see what's inside.
If you remember, we had the token canister and the token asset,
so this is the frontend and this is the backend. And it's pretty simple in that it keeps track of everyone's
balances.
It allows you to query the balance of somebody,
it allows you to pay out from the faucet and also transfer to someone else.
This is going to be the function that we're going to be tapping into.
So you can imagine this is a live deployed project,
then this token canister will be available on the internet computer blockchain, and our OpenD will
also be on the blockchain.
And it's really important for us to learn how to get our canisters to talk to other canisters. Before
we go ahead and deploy this token project and use it,
I want you to take a look inside the read me and take a look at the deploy section.
So the first thing we want to do is to find out our principal ID.
So open up a new terminal inside TOKEN-LOCAL so that you're actually working with it here and then paste
in that command line command so that you've got hold of your current command line user principal.
And then I want you to go into the main.mo which is inside the token folder.
And I want you to replace the part where it says owner with your own principal ID,
so just simply copy it from the terminal and then paste it in here, making sure that it's inside a
set of double quotes, like I've got right here.
Now, next, we're going to go ahead and deploy this project with dfx deploy,
so making sure that your dfx start is hopefully running on your OpenD project.
Now once that's complete, we're going to continue in the next step of the Read Me, which is to go
ahead and start the frontend.
So I'm going to go ahead and run NPM start.
And notice that because we've got our OpenD project running on localhost 8080, automatically npm start
will assign this frontend for TOKEN-LOCAL to a different address so it becomes localhost 8081.
So you can either copy that or you can simply type it in to the command line.
And if you head over there, you'll see our familiar frontend for our token project. Now as we did before,
the first thing we need to do with our token project is to load up the token canister with some DANGs.
So we're going to check and set the canister ID to a local variable.
Go ahead and open up another terminal screen and paste that in there.
So now that we've got the principal ID of the token canister saved inside canister public key, we're
going to transfer half a billion tokens over by calling the token transfer function.
And once that's done, then we can claim the tokens from the faucet by going over here and clicking
on Gimme, Gimme.
And once that comes back as success, then our anonymous user who's operating the frontend should now
have 10,000
DANG.
And we're going to be using these 10,000 DANG in order to purchase NFTs on our OpenD website.
Now I've simplified the project a lot because none of these things are running through internet identity.
We don't have to do the login flow,
we don't have to deploy our canisters, and we're saving ourselves a lot of money because every time
we mint an NFT, that's going to cost us something like $5.
So we're doing a lot of testing for now, but everything that works here will work once we deploy it
online.
And we're just learning how to talk to other canisters that are live and deployed on the Internet computer.
Now that we've given our anonymous user our 10,000 DANG, we're going to call the transfer function.
We're going to use the functions in our faucet backend in order to transfer the money from the buyer
to the seller. In order to access the types and the functions that is in the token backend, we need
to copy the declaration file for our token canister.
Now if you are plugging into somebody else's live canister, they should provide you with this so that
you're able to work with it.
But because we made both of these ourselves, then it's pretty easy for us to simply just copy this
folder,
so right-click copy, and then head over to OpenD. Inside the declarations folder,
go ahead, right-click and paste.
And now you should see we've got our NFT canister, our
opend canister and are token canister.
Don't worry about it being red.
That's just related to the git commit and it doesn't affect us at all.
If you take a look inside the tokendid.
js,
you can see that we're creating an idlFactory here that defines which methods we can call on this
token canister and what data types it expects in the inputs and outputs.
This idlFactory is how we're going to be able to work with that canister in our item.js. Similar
to before, where we imported the idlFactory from our programmatically created NFT containers,
we're going to import the idlFactory from our token.did.
So we're going to type import idlFactory from, and then the location is going to be ../
../../declarations/token.
In order for these two to not conflict with each other,
we're going to give this an alias.
So we're going to say import idlFactory as tokenIdlFactory.
This way we can use it and we'll know the difference. Down here in our handleBuy button,
we're going to create our token actor.
So we're going to use the same agent and local host as we have before, but we're going to use the create
actor to create our token canister.
So heading down here, we're going to create a new constant called tokenActor.
And we're going to set it to equal await
Actor.
create
And inside here, we first are going to provide the token idlFactory.
And then we're going to provide a object with the agent,
and then comma,
and then the canister ID
which is going to be set to the actual ID of our token canister.
So let's get hold of the token canister for our token local project.
And all we have to do is type in dfx canister id token.
And hit enter and we should get back our token id, which we're going to go ahead and put into here.
So we're going to use the principal.fromText
and pass in this id as a string right here.
Now, we can use this token actor and tap into it in the same way that we've been using the OpenD,
so for example, calling the canister methods like so. The main thing that we're interested in is
transferring the money from the buyer to the seller.
So first we have to get hold of the seller's principal ID,
which I'm going to call the sellerId.
And we have a method of getting hold of the original owner of the NFT already in our main.mo,
which is called getOriginalOwner, passing in the ID of the NFT.
That's what we're going to be calling here.
So we're going to say await opend. and then I'm going to paste in that method and pass in the ID
of the NFT which is held inside props.id.
Now the next thing we need in order to make the transfer is to know the itemPrice, to know how much
money to transfer,
right?
And similarly in our main.mo, we've got a method called getListedNFTPrice and it takes the
ID of the NFT
so we can check that as well.
So await opend. paste in the method name and then pass in props.
id
once more.
Now finally, we're ready to make the actual transfer.
So now we can go ahead and use our await, tap into our token actor and call the method here
inside our token canister, which is called transfer.
Transfer takes a to, which is the first input and the amount as a natural number.
If we go ahead and call our transfer and the to is of course the sellerId because they're the ones
who should be benefiting from the sale.
And then the itemPrice is going to be the amount.
And because this transfer function actually returns a piece of text to let us know what's the result
of the transfer, we can actually console.log that as well.
Now let's try it out.
We know that our frontend user has this many DANGs.
And we know that this item costs 2
DANG.
So if I go ahead and click buy, then buy was triggered and hopefully once we get back success from the
result of the transfer, then we can head back over to our faucet, check the balance again and see
that 2 dang was subtracted from the balance.
So that is working as expected.
Now all that's left to do is to simply transfer over the ownership of the NFT
once this transfer result is successful. We can add an if statement and check that the result is equal
to success.
And then inside this if statement, we can transfer the ownership.
To do that, we have to head over to our main.
mo
and create a new public function.
So it's going to be public shared
(msg) func, and we're going to call this completePurchase.
It's going to take three inputs.
Firstly, is the id of the NFT that's in question,
second is the ownerId,
who we''re going to transfer it from,
and thirdly is the newOwner
Id.
And finally, we'll return a piece of text as the result, as usual. Adding the semicolon when needed,
we should end up with our function ready to go.
Now the first thing we have to pull up is the purchased NFT.
So we'll pull it out of our map of Nfts and we'll need to unwrap it from its optional type.
So I'm going to call this a purchasedNFT, which is going to have the data type of the NFTActorClass
.NFT and it's going to be equal to the switch using the mapOfNFTs
.get passing in the id. Now when the case is null, we're going to simply exit this function and
return a piece of text saying NFT does not exist.
But in the case where it does exist, we're going to unwrap the result and return it as the purchased
NFT.
Now, in order to get rid of all of these errors, I'm just going to add a return success at the end
just so that we can continue working on our function unharassed.
The next thing we're going to do is we're going to go ahead and transfer the NFT over to the new owner.
So we're going to call the transfer method on this particular NFT that we pulled up.
So I'm going to say purchasedNFT.
and then if we take a look inside our nft.mo, you can see we've got our transfer ownership method
that expects a new owner as an input.
So we're going to pass over the newOwner
Id as the transfer ownership input. And if the result that comes back from transferResult is success,
then we're going to continue with deleting this item from our mapOfListings and also removing it from
the previous owner's registered list of owned and NFTs.
So firstly, we're going to tap into our mapOfListings and we're going to call the delete function
that is available in a HashMaps, and we're going to pass over the id of the NFTto delete.
The next thing we're going to get hold of is the list of NFTs that the previous owner owned.
So we can delete it from that list.
So I'm going to create a variable called ownedNFTs which is going to be a list of principals.
So List.List, .
And we're going to need to use the switch statement in order fetch it from our mapOfOwners using the
get method and passing in the ownerId.
In the case where it is
null,
then we are going to simply return an empty list.
So List.nil with the data type of Principal.
So this is just going to be an empty list,
and then add the parentheses to initialize that.
And then in the case where we can unwrap it, we are going to unwrap it.
Now the final thing we're going to do is we're going to take this list of NFT Ids that the previous
owner owned, and we're going to run a function called filter on it.
In the documentation, you can see that delete is pretty simple.
It simply deletes the entry with a particular key.
It doesn't do anything if the key doesn't exist.
And on the list data type, we've got something called filter, which will create a new list with
only the elements of the original list for which the given function returns
true.
So basically we can pass in a list and pass in a function.
And if that function returns true as it loops through each of the items in the list, then it's going
to add that item into the new list.
So I'll show you what it looks like in practice.
We're going to say List.filter,
that's the method call.
The first item that we pass in is the list that we want to filter through, which is our ownedNFTs.
Now the second input is going to take a function which loops through each of the NFT Ids, which I'm
going to call listItemId.
And these ids are going to be principal data types.
And for each of these ids, it's going to do some stuff checking to see if it matches the id of this
current NFT.
And if it doesn't, then we're going to return
true
which means it'll get added to the new list.
But if it does, then we'll return
false
and the simplest way to write this logic is to say return when the listItemId does not equal to the
id of the item.
So now we can assign this back into the ownedNFT list.
So we can say ownedNFTs :=
and that means that it will update to this filtered list.
So you can imagine that as it loops through all of the list items, for each of the list items they get
checked.
And if that list item does not equal the ID of the NFT that's being purchased, then we're going to
return
true.
Otherwise, we're going to return false.
When true is returned, then that particular NFT id will get added to the new list.
And if it returns false, then that particular id will be omitted from the new list.
And finally, we're going to add this to the ownership map of the new owner.
So we can use our method that we've really got here, which is called addToOwnership map passing in
the new owner and the ID.
And make sure that you've got that outside of this filter function.
Now, finally, once all of that is done, we're going to return success,
if it all went successfully.
And in the else statement, in case the transfer result was not success, we're simply going to return
the transferResult so that we can see what is the problem.
And taking a glance up here, I've got an error here that says type of Text does not have expected type
async text.
So the reason is because this is missing an await because we have to call this asynchronously.
And that should get rid of that error.
This error is because I've mistyped. It's actually called the newOwnerId rather than the newOwner.
And now I think we should be good to go so we can copy the name of this method,
go back to our item.jsx and actually perform the transfer.
So we're going to say opend. and then paste in the name of our method.
And let me just check the order of inputs.
It's the id, the ownerID and the newOwnerId.
So the id is props.id, the ownerId is this sellerId that we've got here.
And the newOwnerId is the current user id. And we're going to call this with an await and we're going
to capture the result.
Now finally I'm going to console.log this results with purchase...
And let's go ahead and try this out.
So I'm going to hit save and I'll need to redeploy.
So let's go way up to the top of our read me and copy the deploy code here,
paste that in there run our deploy.
Once everything's been deployed, we're going to need to mint an NFT from the command line in order
to buy it.
So I'm going to copy all of this code and then paste it in here and hopefully we'll get a success
back with the principal ID of the newly minted canister.
So I'm going to replace this with that principle, and then we're going to run this command to list
the item for sale.
Once that comes back as success,
I'm going to get hold of my OpenD's canister ID and I'm going to copy that and put it into this fourth
step here.
And it's going to be the part where it says principal something, something.
And I also have to copy this principal of the NFT canister and paste it into here where it says dfx
canister call.
So after all of that, let's go ahead and hit enter.
So now we're ready to test our code.
So I'm going to go ahead and click on the buy button.
And you can see that we get purchase success.
And now if I refresh this Discover page, it should have disappeared from this page.
And when I go into My NFTs, I should see that item listed in there.
Now, I've made quite a few purchases just testing this,
but you should, if you head over to the token frontend, be able to check the before and after token
balance of your account.
And it should go down by 2 each time when you try to purchase one of these NFTs depending on its cost.
Now the final thing we need to address is just some UI issues so that when we purchase our NFT, it disappears
from the Discover page.
And for the loader to show up when the purchase process is undergoing.
So we're going to be reusing some of the things that we had from before.
For example, when the handleBuy is triggered, we're going to set the loader hidden property to false
to bring up our loader.
And then it's going to go through all of this purchasing process.
And once it's completed,
then we're going to go ahead and set our loader to hidden once more.
The next thing I want to do is to make the NFT item disappear from the Discover page once it's been
bought.
So to do that, we're going to add a new style to our top-level div in our item.jsx.
Just before the class name of the first div, I'm going to add my style property, and inside here we're
going to use a little bit of JavaScript to determine whether or not this thing actually displays or
not.
There is a CSS property called display which we can set, and if we set this to none, then you'll
see that it will disappear, even though it's actually there
if we take a look inside the elements. If you go inside the route and inside our gallery view, you can
see that we've got our item and all of the divs that correspond to our item, but it doesn't show up
because we've set the display to be none.
You can either set this display to none or you can set it to inline, which will show it which is what
its original display setting is.
But we're going to use a ternary operator here for the display and we're going to use a variable called
shouldDisplay.
And if it is true, then we're going to use the inline property, and if it's false then we're going
to use none,
so n-o-n-e. And we're going to keep track of the shouldDisplay constant up here.
And setDisplay.
And we're going to set it to true to begin with.
So it should in fact display the item normally, but we're going to use the setDisplay once the purchase
has gone through successfully.
So down here in our handleBuy right at the very end, we're going to set the display to false and that's
going to make that item disappear once it's been purchased.
So we can test all of that out by going through our read me and minting our NFT, copying our principal over to
list it.
And finally, we're going to put this principal into here to call that canister and transfer the ownership
to my OpenD canister, which I hope has not changed.
So I'm going to go ahead and do that.
And now I will see my new NFT ready to be purchased.
And check out what happens this time.
So just to show you that the account actually does change,
currently I've got 9,988 DANG.
I'm going to click Buy.
I've got my loader showing up and once the purchase process goes through, that item is removed from
the gallery.
And if we check our faucet, you can see it went down by 2
DANG and I transferred the money to the original owner of the NFT and I should now be able to view my
NFT in the My NFTs section.
And we have now pretty much completed this entire project.
I can already think of many, many things that you could think about doing to improve the project.
But this has been a really, really long and very big project, which is why in each of the steps, I've
actually included the code that you can run in case you run into any problems.
While building this project, I had many, many, many bugs.
And I wanted to show you some of those bugs just so that in case you see those error messages, you'll
just think to yourself, ah, I saw that in the video and you'll know what to do.
But the truth is, working with the Motoko backend and the internet computer and plus React frontend,
it is a complex, complex project and I fully expect you to have many, many things to debug and to
figure out.
But hey, that's all the part of the fun of learning programming, right?
But at the end, once you persevere through, it's actually a pretty cool website. We're able to mint
NFTs, we're able to list them for sale, we're able to buy them and keep track of the NFTs that we
own and it has a lot of the core functionality of a digital marketplace like Opensea that is running on
the Internet computer.
Now, if you have a lot of money and you want to deploy this project, then feel free to do that.
But just a word of warning that every single time you mint an NFT and you test anything on the deployed
version, then it's going to cost real money and it actually can eat down your balance quite a lot.
Which is why I've tried to keep it in localhost so that we can all learn the things we need to learn
before we start putting up a big budget.
But remember that Dfinity has a really generous developer grant scheme.
So if you think of a project that you think would be really awesome on Dfinity, be sure to go through
the portal and submit a grant application where they can give you lots and lots of support and also
cycles to be able to develop something that is valuable to either people working with the Internet computer
or just as a standalone, decentralized app.
So I hope you enjoyed building this and many of the other projects along with me, and I look forward
to seeing all the great things that you're going to be creating with your imagination in the future.
So until next time.
That's all from me.