All right.
So now that we've seen what some of the vulnerabilities might be for hashed passwords, it's time to
level up and learn about a way that we can prevent these types of dictionary attacks or hash table cracks.
And in order to do that, we have to learn about salting.
Now what exactly is salting?
Well, we already know what hashing is,
it's when we take a password, we run it through a hash function, and we end up with a hash that we
store on our database.
And as we saw in the last lesson, passwords that are generated by humans are extremely insecure.
They tend to be very short, and they tend to be dictionary words that are extremely easy to look up
and create a hash table for.
Now salting takes the hashing a little bit further.
In addition to the password, we also generate a random set of characters and those characters, along
with the user's password, gets combined and then put through the hash function, so the resulting hash
is created from both the password as well as that random unique salt.
So that means no matter how simple the password of the user is, adding that salt increases its complexity,
increases the number of characters, and we make our user database a lot more secure.
Consider the previous problem that we saw in the last lesson, where we covered Hacking 101.
Now we know that three of our users have the same password, and we figured that out because they all
had the same hash,
now, on the other hand, if we had generated a random set of characters, which is the salt, and combined
the password with the salt in order to generate the hash, then they won't have the same hash in our
user database.
So let's try and generate Emily's hash from her password so we know that her password is qwerty and
we generate a random salt.
So then let's go ahead and put in her password qwerty,
and then we append at the end that random salt that we generated.
And we end up with a hash.
Now this hash however, is not the same as Tony's hash or Angela's hash, because the salt is different
each time.
Now the salt is something that the user doesn't have to remember, and instead it's stored in the database
along with the hash.
So that means when the user types in their password, when they try to log in, you combine their password
with the salt.
And if you generate the same hash, then they must have had the same password.
It's kind of clever, isn't it?
And on our database, of course, we wouldn't be storing their passwords, but only the salt and the
hash.
Now consider our previous statistics.
You can generate about 20 billion MD5 hashes per second.
So even if we added a salt and we made it harder to generate a hash table with some of the latest GPUs,
you can still probably generate a hash table with all salt combinations relatively quickly.
So what else can we do to increase the security?
Well, we can use something other than MD5, right?
Another hashing algorithm that's valued because it's incredibly slow.
And this is where Bcrypt comes in.
This is one of the industry standard hashing algorithms that developers use to keep their users' passwords
safe.
Because while you can calculate 20 billion MD5 hashes per second, even the latest and the greatest
GPUs can still calculate only about 17,000 Bcrypt hashes per second, which makes it dramatically harder
for a hacker to generate those precompiled hash tables and a salted hash table instead of taking something
like three seconds if it was hashed with MD5, if it was hashed using Bcrypt, it would take you something
like eight months, which is not really worth a hacker's while.
They'll probably go and search out a company that has less security enabled, and to make our passwords
even more secure when we're using Bcrypt, it has a concept of what's called salt rounds, how many
rounds you're going to salt your password with.
And obviously, the more rounds you do, the saltier your password, and also the more secure it is
from hackers.
What exactly are salt rounds?
Well, let's say that our original user password was qwerty, and we generate a random set of characters
as the salt.
So now we have qwerty and a random set of salt.
We pass it through our hash function Bcrypt and we end up with a hash,
now that's
one round of salting,
if we wanted to have two rounds of salting, then we take the hash that was generated in round one and
we add the same salt from before,
and now we run it through Bcrypt the hash function again, and we end up with a different hash.
And the number of times you do this is the number of salt rounds.
Now the reason why this is genius is because as computers get faster, remember that Moore's Law says
that every year the number of transistors in a computer chip almost doubles, and the cost of that faster
computer halves.
So every year you can get more computing power for less money.
And this is where salt rounds comes in,
when you're hashing your passwords using Bcrypt, you can set the number of rounds you want to salt
your password.
So that means maybe this year in 2019 you salt it 10 rounds, but maybe next year you can increase
that number to 12.
And for every increase in that number, the amount of time that it takes to hash your password doubles.
And so that means you don't have to change your hashing algorithm or update your code, other than simply
changing one number to keep up with the times.
So just to review, coming back to that user database, we'll have each user's username stored,
we'll have their randomly generated salt stored, and then we'll store their hash after a set number
of salting rounds.
And when it comes to checking their password, when they log in, we'll take the password that they
put in, combine it with the salt that's stored in the database, and run it through the same number
of salting rounds until we end up with the final hash, and we compare the hash against the one that's
stored in the database to see if they've entered the correct password.
Let's give that a go in real life and implement Bcrypt and salting rounds into our website's authentication.
The package that we're going to be using to hash our passwords using Bcrypt is also called bcrypt,
and you can find the documentation for it, as always on NPM.
Now let's try and apply this knowledge to our project, and add hashing and salting into our password
storage and make it a little bit more secure.
Go ahead and download and extract the project file for this lesson.
And once you have extracted it and opened it in VS Code, it should be 9.2 Authentication Lv.2,
take a look inside the index.js, you'll see that we have all of the code that came from the solution
code at the end of the previous lesson.
So there's no hashing or anything happening here just yet,
and we're going to implement that very quickly.
Take a look inside the package.json,
you'll notice that there is a new dependency added,
and that's bcrypt.
Bcrypt is a way for us to be able to hash our passwords using the Blowfish algorithm, which is a super
secure, very modern way of ensuring that nobody with current computational skills should be able to
decode our password in a reasonable amount of time.
It is something that is industry standard, and we're going to use it in our project.
As always, first of all, cd into the correct project and then use "npm install" to add all of the node
modules.
All right.
So the first thing we need to do is to import that bcrypt module.
So, import bcrypt from "bcrypt";
And one thing we should define before we start using it is the number of salting rounds.
So we'll call that saltRounds,
and I'm going to set it to 10.
It depends on your own individual sort of level of security you want for your app,
but obviously, as we explained, the more rounds of salting that happens, the more computation and more
time therefore is required to try and hack the original password out of the hash.
So if we only did two salt rounds, it would take less time to generate the hash,
but it would also probably allow some bad actors to be able to figure out the original password by brute
forcing a lot quicker.
So we've imported bcrypt,
we've added our number of salt rounds,
the next thing we're going to do is to actually use it. Coming into our register POST route right here,
we've got all of our previous code,
but now after we check and make sure that the user doesn't already exist and we're about to save their
email and password into our database, just before that happens, we're going to do our password hashing,
and we're going to do that by using the bcrypt module
and it has a method called hash().
Now this method takes a number of inputs.
So the first one is the data that you want to hash, which is the password that the user typed into
the form.
Next is the number of salt rounds.
So we already have that defined as a constant up top which I said 10 in my case,
and it works out on a couple of computers
we tried to be good enough in terms of speed.
And then finally we have our callback which can return an error, and if there were no errors, then
it will return the encrypted string, which we're going to call the hash.
So let's create this callback.
And once we have that hash then the next step is to store that into our database instead of the plain
text password.
So I'm going to take all of this code up to the res.render()and put it inside this callback.
Now remember that because we are waiting on this query to complete without any errors, before we
res.render(secrets.ejs), we have to turn this callback into an asynchronous method by adding the async
keyword before it.
So now we're ready to replace this password with the hash that gets generated here.
And if there were any errors through the hashing process, then we need to either handle it or at the
very least we need to console.log() it just so that while we're testing, we know what's going on.
And if there were no errors, then we're going to go ahead and do the rest of the planned parts of saving
that user's hash and email into our database.
Let's go ahead and try this out.
Let's go ahead and start our index.js.
Go back to our website.
Go to the home page.
Try to register a new user.
So I'm just going to call it maybe test.
And then the password is still the same.
It's 123456.
And then I'm going to click Register.
So now if I go to my database and I right-click on the users to View all of them, I should now have
a new user, test@gmail.com,
and the password,
as you can see, even though as you saw me enter it, it was still 123456.
Just public announcement,
"Don't do that."
Try to have a more secure password.
But even though it's super insecure in terms of password, we now have a hash that's generated.
It's super long.
I definitely cannot tell that this is one, two three, four, five, six, and hopefully nobody else
will be able to do, if we managed to do everything correctly.
And that's because we did our hashing correctly.
So now somebody hacks into our database, they'll see this instead of this
and it means we've made life a little bit safer for this user.
I'm going to go ahead and actually delete this first entry for angela@gmail.com, because it no longer
actually follows our password strategy.
So now every new user that gets signed up on our website will have a hash for their password.
Now that we've done our registration and we've hashed our password for storage, the next step is to
figure out how to compare the password that's stored in the database against the password that the user
enters when they try to log in.
Unfortunately, with bcrypt, because we're doing many salting rounds, each time we hash the password,
it will not match.
So we can't simply just compare the stored hash against the hashed version of the login password and
expect them to match.
There's actually an extra layer of security in there with that salting, and each time the hash that's
generated will be different.
How can we then compare those two passwords?
Well, Bcrypt actually comes with a method called compare.
Right here we're going to say bcrypt.
and this is the method that we want to use which is compare().
And this allows us to compare the data which is the data that is to be encrypted.
So the data that comes from the user when they try to log in and then the encrypted, which in this
case is of course the hash that's stored in our database,
and then we end up returning a callback.
So bcrypt.compare,
and the first one is the new password.
So I'm just going to change this to loginPassword so that we're not confused later on in our compare.
So we're comparing the login password,
and we're going to compare it against the result that comes back here which I'm going to change to the
"storedHashedPassword".
And that's the comparison that's going to be made.
Now the order of these two matters a great deal.
So don't put this one here and that one here.
It has to be this way
so that the compare() method knows which one it needs to work with and which one needs to hash.
And then we end up with our callback, which is going to be an error or a result,
and then here we can again handle any errors that occur in this process by console logging.
And if there were no errors, then we're simply going to check to make sure that the result is valid.
Then we're going to console.log(result)
for now. I just want to show you what it actually looks like.
So let's go back to our login page.
Use the user that has a hash password.
Go back to here.
You can see that what got console logged is the result, "true"
which means that all we need to do is to check if that is true,
then we can go ahead and res.render(),
but if it's false then we can again send that they got the incorrect password.
And we can now delete this if and else statement here.
Just to make sure,
let's try that with a wrong password.
I'm going to use the second worst password in the world, which is qwerty.
Click log in.
You can see we get incorrect password.
There you have it.
We've now implemented hashing and salting, and we have made our passwords much, much more secure for
our users.
And even if somebody hacks into our website, they will only be able to see this<
and there is no way for them to be able to get back the original password that's associated with that
email.
And if you want to allow users to log in with email and password, we're at a stage where that's already
pretty secure for the user.
In the next lesson, I'm going to talk about something slightly different.
We're going to talk about how to implement cookies and sessions so that when a user is logged in, they
can log in to access the secret page, but that login is saved as a cookie so that they don't have to
re-log in
if they came back to the website, say within a certain period of time.
And this is pretty common when you try to access Facebook or Gmail, you're not having to enter your
password again and again each time.
And we're going to be able to add that functionality to our website as well.
Keep your eyes peeled in the next lesson as we learn all about that.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.