Hey guys, in this lesson, I want to introduce you to the concept of environment variables.
And again, similar to the previous lesson, this is not so much about our users about keeping their
data safe.
It's more about keeping your data safe.
So what do I mean by that?
In the last lesson you saw that we created session and we had to create an encryption key, a secret.
And keeping that secret in our index.js, which, as you may know, is often uploaded to GitHub.
Or you might need to put that onto your server.
Either way, that information is very, very easily leaked.
It's very easy for people to crawl GitHub looking out for these secrets and API keys that they can take
advantage of.
And very often in the development world, you hear stories like this where a developer put AWS keys
on GitHub.
Then bad things happen.
And it's because currently we're in a bitcoin mining frenzy era.
And to mine Bitcoin, you need a lot of computing resources.
And those resources get directly turned into money, providing a huge incentive for people to scrape
the internet for developers who've accidentally published their secret keys.
And this is a good story as well, that, um, I'll link to in the course resources, where this guy
Luke had accidentally published his API keys onto GitHub, and then he racked up an AWS bill of over
$3,000 in a very, very short space of time.
Now, I think the ending to the story was a happy one.
An Amazon AWS actually refunded him the money, but I'm not sure everybody is as lucky as he was.
These are some really cautionary tales about keeping your secrets, your API keys off the internet,
where it's publicly searchable, where people can steal.
That's all very well and good, but how exactly do we do that?
Because obviously for our app to work, we need these secrets to be able to encrypt our database.
And for us to be able to collaborate with other people or simply just using version control or backing
up our project to GitHub, then we will need to publish it.
Right?
So the way that developers solve this conundrum is through using something called environment variables.
What exactly are these environment variables used for?
Well, there's two major use cases.
One is for convenience.
Normally when you deploy a large application, the process is quite complicated.
And once you've done it, you kind of don't want to mess around with the code base and update the code
files.
Instead, you could have these environment variables which you can change so certain variables that
are being used in your code base could be set as environment variables, and you could modify those
variables without having to touch the code.
A second reason might be for security.
So when you're developing software, you might be uploading your code base somewhere.
And it's usually not a good idea to have things like your authentication keys or your API keys to be
stored in the same place as the rest of your code.
That's where environment variables come in.
So environment variables essentially allows us to separate out where we store our keys, our secret
stuff, and various other variables away from where our code base is located.
Environment variables are basically a very, very simple file that we're going to keep certain sensitive
variables, such as encryption keys and API keys.
In this lesson, I want to show you how we can do this using a really popular package called dot env.
And you can see just through the sheer number of weekly downloads that it is a really heavily dependent
upon module to keep everybody's secrets off of the internet safe and secure.
All right.
So let's get started and see how we can implement environment variables in our project and save those
secrets and keep the secrets secret.
Go ahead and download and extract the folder called 9.4 Environment Variables.
And if you look inside package.json, the package that we're using to create these environment variables
is called dot env.
If you're not already there, then stop your server CD over to this particular module and go ahead and
run npm install to install that new package.
Once you've done that, the next step we need to do in order to move this secret out of our index.js
is to create a file inside this folder.
So at the top level so you can collapse the folder, open the folder.
And here you're going to click on this button to add a file.
Now whereas normally files end with an extension like dot jpeg or dot png.
In this case we're only going to give the file an extension name and it's dot e env.
And if you get it right you should see that on the left hand side you get this little gear icon.
Show up.
Now if you don't see any of these icons on your VSCode, it's probably because you don't have this extension
installed.
It's free.
We covered it at the beginning of the course, but it's called VSCode icons, and you can add that and
it'll give you these pretty little icons to work with.
So how do we move this out?
Well, literally I am just going to cut my secret and paste it into here.
Now I'm going to give it a name.
I'm going to call it session Underscore secret.
And this allows us to see some of the formatting of how environment variables are added.
First we have a name for that variable.
And notice how there's no constructor in front of it.
There's no const or var or whatever.
This is not actually JavaScript.
This is just a way for us to give this piece of information a name.
And everything is in all caps, and each word is separated by an underscore.
And then we have an equal sign.
And then we have a string enclosed in double quotes.
That string is going to be whatever information is going to be associated with that name.
The other thing to notice is that there's no space between the start and the end of the equal sign.
And also, if you were to create another variable here, you don't have any sort of commas or semicolons
or anything.
You just start it on a new line.
Now that we've got that, let's go ahead and save that.
Go back to our index.js.
What do we replace this part with?
Well, we replace it with process which is a NodeJS process tapping into env which is an environment
variable property, and it contains the user environment.
And then we tap in to the name that we gave it, which in my case was session to S's underscore secret.
And this should tap into the environment that this current file is run in in the node process.
And it tries to find the one that has this particular name right here.
Now, in order to add this file into that environment, we need to use that dot env module that we imported
earlier.
So we're going to import env from dot m.
Like so.
And then we need to also initialize it.
So we're going to write env dot config.
And this is the one where it adds the dot env file contents into the process dot env so that we can
actually have access to it.
And that's all it takes to set up an environment variable.
So now if we go ahead and run our code so we'll do index.js.
And we go to our localhost and we log in.
Everything still works exactly the same as before.
And we still have our sessions persisting etc., but we no longer have that secret right here in the
index.js for anyone to read.
This is useful when we start thinking about things like professional development.
We would have this probably under source control.
So if you go into this tab here in VS code, you'll see initialized repository which you can click on
which will initialize a new source control or in this case a new git repository for our project.
And it can persist all of the things that you want to persist.
Now, this includes all of the things that I have in all of the other projects, which is a little bit
much, but it's essentially based on the top level.
Now, what usually happens when you upload your files to GitHub or any other form of source control,
or something like this, you normally will add the dot env file type to the git, ignore a completely
separate file that's added to a git ignore list, which means that when we upload our project to GitHub
or any other form of git, it doesn't go online where it could be seen by others, which means it does
not get added to git and given access to other people.
To see.
If you take a look at this URL or simply just search for GitHub node, the GitHub team themselves have
actually come up with a list of common things that you should probably ignore if you're making a node
project, and these things include things which are very large, such as any node modules, because
all the dependencies are added together, is a ton of code.
You don't want to be uploading downloading that.
That's why I always get you to do npm install just to get used to the practice, even though we're downloading
through zip files.
But in the future, if you're working on open source projects, if you're working in a company, you're
very often going to be pulling data from a GitHub repository or pushing data to GitHub.
And it's important that you don't end up uploading this up and down all the time.
Now, the other thing that you'll see in here, which makes sense for us, is our dot env files.
So you can add other types of dot env.
So you can specify one which is just for local development, one which is for production local etc.
but the one that we care about the most is pretty much the bog standard dot env.
And this is also ignored for git, which is important.
So let me just demo to you what this actually looks like.
So I'm going to copy this file.
And I'm going to create a new window where I'm going to create a new project.
So here's a brand new project.
Let me just go ahead and create something.
Let's say we CD to the desktop and I make deer create git env test.
And we go into that.
So open that folder.
And we open it in our VS code.
Let me just create something code not so secret dot js.
And then inside here we can have whatever it is we want.
Um I'm just going to have some text in here.
And then I'm going to add a dot env file which is going to contain my top top top secrets.
And now I'm going to create this as a repository.
So in the source control tab I'm going to create repository I'm going to create an initial commit I'm
going to stage everything.
And I'm going to publish this branch to a public GitHub repository under my username.
So now I should be able to open it up inside GitHub.
And you will see both of these things dot env and not so secret.
So dot env contains all of my top top secrets which I don't want anybody to know about.
And this is really, really bad for me.
So let's do it properly this time.
Let's show you how we should be doing things.
So let's go ahead and CD back and I'm going to make a new directory.
Let's call this proper way to get Env.
There we go.
And let's go ahead and open that up here instead.
And in here I'm going to again use my let's say we have our index.js which needs to exist, have some
code, whatever it may be.
And then we have our next file which is our dot env containing our top secrets.
And now what I'm going to do is actually create my.
Gitignore.
So it is simply dot git ignore one word no spaces.
And then I'm going to copy all of these things from that repository that GitHub created.
Paste it in here, save this and then go to my source control initialize repository.
As I have done before.
Commit.
Add everything to staging and then publish the branch to a public repository.
Once that's done, let's go ahead and open it up in GitHub and you can see that thankfully this time
I didn't have to remember to remove my env or to remove any of the other things because my git ignore
already tells me don't upload these terribly secret things, and that means I don't end up with somebody
stealing my API keys, which is very important.
So let these stories serve as a warning and remember to always think about adding a dot.
Gitignore file.
Whenever you start thinking about using git, which should be at the very beginning.
Anyways, in this lesson you've seen how we can use the dot env package to add files in the dot env
file to the local variable, but I want you to have a little go practicing this.
If you take a look at the other part of our code, which really should probably be in environment variables
is our database setup.
Now normally your database would not be localhost, it would be hosted remotely.
So anybody with the database access the username and the password would be able to access that database,
which is not what you want.
So let's prepare for this by switching out the user, the host, the database, the password and the
port all into environment variables.
See if you can remember how to do this and we'll run through it together.
All right.
So remember that every single new environment variable has to go on a new line.
And I'm going to paste in something I made earlier just to speed things up a bit for you.
And I'm giving a description.
This is PG Postgres user host database password and port.
I've saved each of those values as a string.
No spaces anywhere.
And now I can go back into my database and replace all of this plain text in here with process dot env
dot.
In this case it's pg underscore user.
And you can go through that process for the rest of the lines.
So now if somebody looked at our index.js they would say wow, there's all of this secret information
that I can't get access to.
I don't know what your password is.
I don't know what your session secrets are.
This doesn't tell me anything that I can do anything bad with.
And that's exactly what we want.
So hopefully you will have seen how environment variables work.
And if you're working with any project which requires a API key, especially one which is paid, remember
this lesson and come back to it if necessary.
In the next lesson, we're going to get back on to upgrading the security level of our website.
And instead of storing users passwords ourselves, having to try and make sure people don't hack into
our database, encrypting, salting, hashing, all of that, we're going to put all of that responsibility
onto a big company like Google.
So we're going to learn about Google OAuth.
So for all of that and more I'll see you there.