Hey guys, in this lesson we're going to be upgrading our authentication one more level.
And this is something that you can either have alongside your previous local strategy where you allow
people to authenticate using username, password or email and password.
And you have this alongside or as some modern websites do these days, they don't actually even allow
people to register using username and password or make it really, really small so that people mostly
go for the social logins.
Now what exactly is OAuth?
You might have heard of this terms, but all it is, it's simply a open standard for token based authorization.
Now what did all of that mean?
Well let me explain.
So you've heard of Facebook right.
But let's say that we're building a different web app.
Let's say we're building a social network that's going to be the new Facebook, and it's going to be
called Facebook.
And Bray's book is an awesome social network for people who have braces.
Now, when you're a new user who's signing up for Brace Book, you probably won't have any friends in
the beginning, right?
And nobody likes a social network where you have no social connections and nobody wants to feel like
they have no friends.
So what can we do as the developers of Brace Book to make this process of joining our social network
a little bit easier?
Well, we can ask the user for permission to access their Facebook account and see which friends they
have on Facebook are already users of our service by Facebook.
So now once the user sign up, they'll already see that three of their friends are already on Facebook
and they're ready to get started in a new life of socializing with their B braced friends.
Now, how would this work exactly?
Well, on our login page, we can ask the user to sign in either manually where they don't get the benefit
of instantly connecting with their friends who have braces, or we can get them to log in with Facebook.
And in this case, what would happen is we would make a Get request to Facebook asking them for this
user's friends on Facebook and Facebook would return with a post request with that list of users and
emails.
So this might be a really simplified version of that.
It's just a straight up table of this particular user's friends on Facebook and all of their emails.
So then this gets passed over to our server, where we can compare it against our database of users
and see whether, if we have any matching users who have the same email addresses.
So now we know that for this user, we have three friends of theirs who are already on Facebook, and
we'll be able to automatically add them as a friend onto Facebook.
And it's also a similar scenario if you are signing up to LinkedIn.
For example, if you couldn't be bothered to type in all of your contacts email addresses to find on
LinkedIn and add them individually, then what LinkedIn might do is it asks you to log in via Google,
and it will look through all of your contacts on Gmail in order to add them automatically to LinkedIn.
So by using OAuth, we're able to access pieces of information on these third party websites, such
as their friends emails or their contacts on Gmail.
But in our case, because we're talking about authentication and leveling up the security of our authentication,
another really big benefit involves delegating the task of managing passwords securely to these companies
like Facebook and Google.
As we mentioned before, every day or so yet another company gets hacked, and these companies tend
to be kind of low tech companies, companies that are not Facebook, Google, Amazon who are really
known for having great engineers, great teams who are able to implement all of these levels of security
for the authentication on their website.
And they probably have thought about hashing and salting passwords or other data that they're storing.
But there's more.
There are things such as not only salting the passwords, but also peppering the passwords.
Some companies also encrypt the entire database containing the hashed passwords, and have a wide array
of complex mathematical solutions to keep their user passwords under lock and key.
Now, as a web developer, we could implement all of those things that I just spoke about and address
all of the edge cases, but it would take us a lot of time and a lot of development hours.
So what?
Why not simply delegate this task to a large company like Facebook and Google?
So then every time we log in our user, we simply ask them to log in on Facebook.
And Facebook will then authenticate them using their own secure methods.
And once that's done, Facebook sends us back a message saying this user is authenticated.
There are real Facebook user and they have got their correct username and passwords.
So go ahead and authenticate them as well.
And that will make our lives a lot easier.
We'll have a lot less liability.
And this is the way that you're seeing a lot of websites going where they only have third party login
like login with Twitter, Facebook, Google, GitHub.
But in order for us to be able to do all of this, we need to learn about OAuth.
That is the glue that binds all of this together and makes it actually tick.
Now, what exactly is special about OAuth?
Because there's a lot of other open standards that does something similar to this, but OAuth is quite
special in three ways.
The first way is that it allows you to grant a granular level of access.
What does that mean?
That means that when your user logs in with Facebook, you can request specific things from their Facebook
account.
So you could say that for my app, I only really need their profile and email address.
But say if you were Tinder and you wanted to know who all their friends were so you don't accidentally
match them up, then you might want to know also their list of friends.
So this is what I mean by granularity.
The app developer can determine what kind of data do they need from the user's Facebook account and
request those accordingly.
Now, the second thing about OAuth is it allows for either read only or read and write access.
So in the case of Facebook, this means that you can either ask them to just retrieve pieces of information
about their Facebook account.
So what's their name?
What's their email?
Who are their friends?
Or you can ask for write access as well.
Say for example, in this case, if WordPress wanted to be able to post to Facebook on this user's account,
then they would need to ask for, read and write access.
And the third thing is that the third party that you're using to authenticate your users should be able
to revoke access at any point on their website.
So that means if you're authenticating with Facebook, the user should be able to go into their Facebook
account and de-authorize the access that they granted to your website, say, Facebook, and they don't
actually have to go on to your website where maybe you're less keen to give up this access.
So now that we've looked at what's special about OAuth, the next thing to talk about is, well, how
does it actually work in reality?
So the first step is to actually tell this third party, be it Facebook, Twitter or Google, about
our web application because they don't know about us.
Right?
So we have to set up our app in their developer console, and in return we get what's called an app
ID or a client ID, and we or our website is then the client, which will make the request to Facebook
to authenticate our user.
Now, once you've set up your app, the next step happens when the user tries to log on to your website.
So when the user hits up facebook.com and they want to authenticate, we give them an option to log
in with Facebook.
So once they click on that option, then we'll take them to the actual Facebook website so that they
are seeing a familiar interface, a trustworthy interface, and they will log in to Facebook using their
Facebook credentials.
And without OAuth, what we would have to do is to ask the user, hey, what's your login credentials
for Facebook?
Can you give me your Facebook password?
Nobody wants to do that.
That seems super sketchy and really insecure.
So OAuth makes that step a lot easier because it gets them to log in on the website that they actually
trust, which is Facebook, right?
Something that they've been using for a long time now.
Once the user logs in on this third party, then they have to review the permissions that our website
is asking for.
So for example, you might want your profile and email address and they review that and they're like
okay I'll grant that permission.
So now that they've granted the permission and they've successfully logged in on Facebook, then our
website will receive an authorization code from Facebook.
And this allows us to check to make sure that the user actually successfully signed on to Facebook.
They had the right username and password.
So we're now.
Able to authenticate them and log them on to our website.
But if we wanted to go a step further, we can also exchange our authentication code for an access token.
And when we receive that access token from Facebook, we would save it into our database, because this
is the token that we can use if we want to request for pieces of information.
Subsequently, this access token is valid for a lot longer than the authentication token.
So the way you should see it is that the authentication code or the auth code is kind of like a ticket.
Write a ticket that you're going to use once to enter the cinema, but the access token is kind of more
like a year pass.
And it comes with benefits like backstage access, where you get to request pieces of data from Facebook,
including their friend list or their username or their password, whatever it may be that they granted
you permission to access.
So the auth code is what we need to authenticate the user that they successfully manage the login through
Facebook and the access token is what we'll use to access pieces of information that are stored on that
user's account on this third party's website, for example, their email or their friends list.
All right, so enough theory, let's get started implementing it and adding login with Google to our
website.
Now, hopefully you haven't skipped over the previous text lesson where we showed you how to set up
the Google OAuth credentials.
You'll need those.
And it's very, very important that you follow it step by step and get it to work.
Hopefully, if you have completed that though, you will have filled out your M file and you would have
replaced the placeholders in the Google Client ID and Google Client secret sections.
And once you've done that, then we're ready to go into our index.js and start writing up some code.
Now, hopefully you've already run npm install on this current project, and all of the modules are
installed.
Now, the only new module that we've added into this project in this upgrade is the passport Google
OAuth.
And this is going to allow us to create the Google login strategy.
So we can import the Google strategy from the passport Google OAuth two module.
And we can go ahead and configure it just below our previous passport dot use.
So this is our local strategy.
And just below it we're going to say passport dot use.
And this is going to set up our passport authentication middleware.
And this one is going to be a Google based strategy.
We're going to first give the strategy a name which we'll call Google.
And then we can go ahead and create the actual asynchronous function.
And then we can go ahead and set up our new Google strategy.
The first thing in this strategy is a set of options.
And that includes the client ID, which is going to be set from the process dot env dot Google underscore
client underscore ID.
Let me just double check that I've spelled that correct.
Yep I think that's pretty much the same.
I'm going to copy the next line so I don't have to type it out.
And the next one is called the Client Secret.
Now the spelling of all these things matter a huge deal.
So try to make sure that you haven't got anything that you've made a typo here on.
And if in doubt, you can always check the solution file for exactly how it's meant to be spelled.
And then we have our callback URL, which in our case, if you remember previously we had set to http
colon forward slash forward slash localhost colon 3000.
And then it's forward slash auth forward slash Google forward slash secrets.
And then finally we need to add something called the user profile URL.
And this is actually found right at the bottom of the file.
And this is the one that we're going to use to be able to get hold of the user's profile information.
And there you have it.
We've now set up all of the settings.
So let's add a comma.
And now let's add the callback function which gets triggered once the process succeeds.
So once they actually manage to log in with their Google account, there's something called an access
token which we don't actually need to use.
So also something called a refresh token which we don't need to use.
It's something that can help us keep that user signed in or track their session as we go along.
And then we have something called the profile.
And finally that thing that we use a lot in passport, which is the callback.
Now we are in the same section as what we've got here.
And we can now get hold of parts of the Google profile.
And for now, what I'm going to do is I'm just going to console, log that profile to show you what
it contains.
And we're going to try and get this login page to trigger.
So for that to happen, we of course need a get route to do that.
So just below the end of the other get routes I'm going to write a new App.get.
It's going to be hit up when the user clicks on the new sign up with Google and sign in with Google
buttons in our login and register ejs so it hits up forward slash auth, forward slash Google.
So it's the same for register and login.
We want them to both hit up the same route.
And then we're going to use the passport middleware.
So passport dot authenticate.
And then we're going to specify the strategy we want to authenticate with.
And remember we set up the authentication down here to be called the Google strategy.
So we're going to use that right here.
So passport dot authenticate.
The strategy we want to use is the Google strategy.
And then once that's done then we can go ahead and add in some options.
We're going to say what are the things that we need to get from this login.
And it's going to be the scope.
So this is an array.
We want their profile and we want their email.
So adding both of these things in will mean that when the user logs in we'll tell them we're going to
try and grab hold of your public profile and your email.
Hope that's okay.
If they consent and they log in, then we should be able to receive it down here.
And it should go into this strategy because it's called Google Strategy.
And we specified it here.
This is a good point to note that you probably notice previously that when we authenticated on the login,
we use the passport local authentication method.
And this is an optional thing.
If you only have one strategy, you don't actually have to name it because they're all the same.
But in our case, because we now have two strategies, it's a good idea to add the word local for our
local strategy just before the new strategy gets created, and Google for our Google strategy, so that
when you run the middleware and you say passport dot authenticate, you can specify which strategy the
code should go into, should it go into the Google strategy, which is here, which is going to console
log the profile, or should it go into the local strategy which is going to console, log the username
from the form submission and you'll be able to see this is how these different blocks of code actually
gets triggered.
And this is kind of behind the scenes how passport works.
Let's give this a go.
And hopefully it works.
Let's go ahead and start up our server.
And go to our register screen and click on this new button.
Sign up with Google.
And now I've got the classic Google sign in screen, which I thankfully didn't have to code up.
This all comes from Google, and then I'm going to click to the account that I have a Google sign in
with, and I'm going to go ahead and sign in.
Now notice it says that Google hasn't verified this app.
Now, app verification can take anywhere between one month and three months.
So we're just doing tutorial.
We're keeping it in localhost.
It doesn't actually matter for us in this case.
If you're developing a production app, then you'll need to wait for that process and submit it on that
console platform that I showed you in the previous text lesson.
So in our case, what we're going to do is we're going to click on continue.
And if you accidentally clicked on the right button you can always go back and just click on it again.
So now it's going to say that signing in to this application called secrets.
And by continuing Google share your name, email address and some other profile things with this application
we built the application.
We are receiving the information.
So in our case it doesn't really matter.
We're just doing some testing.
Let's click continue.
And now it's trying to make a Get request to this location which we haven't written in our server yet.
So let's go ahead and do that.
Let's go back to our code and below the previous app.get.
Let's add forward slash auth forward slash Google forward slash secrets.
And in this case we're going to run passport dot authenticate using the Google strategy.
And we're going to add some options.
Just like what we've got down here.
The success redirect and the failure redirect.
So success redirect should similarly as login go to secrets.
And the failure redirect should go also in the same vein as the code below, go to login.
Let's save that code and let's try it again.
Let's go back to our register page.
Sign up with Google.
Click on the account.
Continue.
And now, if we take a look inside our terminal, you'll see that that person's profile has now been
printed into our console.
So includes things like their picture, their name, their email, and a whole bunch of things that
they allowed you to have access to, which we can then save in our application.
That's the next part of the code that we're going to do.
What happens when we end up inside this callback?
How can we save their data into our database and be able to identify them in our system?
First we're going to add a try catch block as we have previously done.
And then we're going to use a await to make a DB query.
And we're going to use the command select all from users where email is equal to dollar one.
And the email is going to come from that profile that we printed out just now.
So it's profile dot email.
And just to verify you can see that we printed out the profile.
And indeed inside the profile there is a property called email which is what we need to save into our
server.
So the first thing we want to check is to create a result that checks to see if that email already exists
in our database.
Now we can use an if statement to check if result dot rows dot length is equal to zero, in which case
that means we don't have any users by that email in our system.
Then we're going to create a new user.
So we're going to again use await db dot query.
And the query in this case is going to be an Insert query.
So we're going to insert into the users table.
And we're going to add to the two columns email and password.
And the values that we're going to add are going to be dollar one and dollar two.
And let's add that at the end.
So dollar one is the email which is easy.
It's profile dot email.
Now what you want to set as their password depends on you.
So some people because there is no password we don't get the user's password from Google.
And that's the whole point of it.
We don't have to store it.
So some people store their user ID to identify them.
Some people store a word such as Google, just so that when you look through the database, you know
why it is they don't have a suitable password is because they are a Google sign in user.
So it really depends.
In my case, I'm going to set it as Google to be able to differentiate them from the local login users
and to make sure that they don't.
Then try to log in with the same email that they logged in using the Google login.
But it really is something that is up to you individually.
Now that we've created the new user, we can now finally use that callback and we're going to pass null
for no errors.
And then we're going to pass the new user into that callback, so that when we serialize and deserialize
that user, we can then access it in the same location when we go to the secrets.
So that requests dot user gets populated with the details that we add in from this new user that we
created.
Remember, with the local login strategy, we get hold of the user that's stored in our database and
add it to the session.
And in our Google strategy, we get hold of the new user that we've just added.
And because this actually is the result from this query, you'll remember that it's not just the result,
it's actually dot rows at position zero.
Next we're going to add a L statement.
And this L statement is in the case where we already have the existing user.
And that's because this is if result equals zero then that means that user is new and we add them in.
But otherwise that means the user already exists.
And we can tap into the result in order to add to the callback.
So we don't force them to log in again.
We also say there's no error and we simply tap in to result dot rows, and we grab the zeroth one as
the user that we register.
So now finally, we can use our catch to catch any errors.
And we can use a callback to pass that error through.
And that is all we need to do in order to set up our Google strategy.
Now, there's quite a few moving parts in this, so I would not be surprised if you made a typo or a
mistake or order or something is wrong.
So what?
I recommend you to do is to use the VS code compare, just to make sure that you haven't made any typos
or any issues.
So you can do this by right clicking on the current file that you're writing.
So your index.js and select this line select for compare.
This is your file.
And then I want you to right click on solution JS and select the other one.
Compare with selected.
I know it's confusing, but just listen to me a few more times and you'll probably understand what's
going on.
But this way we've got our index.js on the left side.
The solution dot JS on the right side, and you'll be able to see any of the differences between your
file and the solution file.
So here are some things that might be different.
If in your file there's something extra, then you'll see it show up as red, meaning this is deleted
in the solution file.
Or if there is something extra on the solution file, you'll see it as green, which means this is something
that's extra compared to your file.
Now, some of these things might just be an order kind of thing.
For example, if I change the order here to here, you'll see it show up as red.
Here line ten is deleted, but line four is added.
And you can read through this just to see what the differences are and be able to understand what's
actually going on.
And the most important part is of course this app.use Google strategy.
So check to see if you have the shouldn't really be anything that's different compared to the solution
code in your case, because we're using Process.env.
So we're not taking into account any of these unique aspects.
That's in your environment variable file.
So hopefully you can match up and find all the issues.
This is a really neat way that I hope will help you, but otherwise we are ready to test things out.
Let's hit save and hopefully Nodemon is still listening.
To all changes and updating things.
Yep.
So let's go to our server and let's go to register sign up with Google.
And if we check our database and update it you'll see the new user has been added in.
So this is the email and this is the password that we set for them.
And now if I go into secrets and I refresh it or I close down the browser and reopen the browser, you'll
see it's still cached my session even though I'm logging in with a Google login.
Now, the final thing we want to do before we finish is we want to make this logout button work, because
otherwise we can't test our other login methods.
But also it's pretty useful for our regular users in passport.
The log out method is really simple.
You'll see if you go into the secrets page, which is where the log out button exists.
It goes to Forward slash log out.
So this will be a get request that we can create in our server.
Going to the end of all of the other get requests.
Let's go ahead and create another app.get.
And we're going to say forward slash logout.
And here we're going to set up our request response callback.
And we're going to tap into the request object.
And there's something in there that's actually called log out.
Now it's important that you choose this one which is all lowercase rather than this one.
And then we can go ahead and add our callback.
So error.
And inside here we're going to check if there is an error.
In which case we will simply just console log the error.
And otherwise we're going to raise redirect to forward slash.
So the home page is where we're going to go after we log out.
If you've never seen this syntax before this is simply just a one liner.
So we've got an if we've got the condition and then we've got what should happen.
If that's true all in one line.
And let's go back to our secrets page.
Let's make sure that we can actually sign in.
And now if we click log out, it takes us to the home page.
And if we try to go to secrets again it's not going to let us.
So there you have it.
We've got login with email password.
We've got login with Google.
And we now have log out.
All that's left to do is for you to be able to show a secret for each user, and for each user to be
able to add their own secrets, and that will complete this project.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.