Hey guys, we finally got into the point where we can actually finish off all of the features for our
secrets application.
We've done a lot in terms of building up the authentication levels, making sure that it's secure,
giving users lots of different ways of signing in, and discovering a secret.
Now, this secret at the moment lives in the secrets dot js file, which is just a piece of text at
the moment, and you can see it if you go into the views secrets dot JS.
It's just a paragraph element.
Now we're going to change all of that.
We're going to use JS to insert a users secret, and the user should be able to submit their own secrets.
There is a page called submitting JS, where we can allow users to make a Post request to a route in
our server which is at forward slash submit in order to submit some text that corresponds to their secret.
And that secret then will get displayed here, and we'll keep it in our database in the same user's
table.
Just to keep things simple.
So your job is to complete this as a challenge by yourself.
The first thing that you're going to need to do is to add a new column to the users table, which has
a name of secret, and it's going to hold data of type text.
And once you're done, the user should be able to log in to the website and click to submit a secret.
This brings up the submit dot ejs page and the user can type a secret.
For example.
What are some of my secrets?
Um, I'm scared of clowns, which is a weird one.
But also, despite learning surfing for so many years, I'm still kind of bad at it.
Which is a secret.
Please don't tell anyone.
And once I hit submit, I'm going to save that secret into the database under that user in the same
row as that user.
And then when secrets gets rerendered, that secret gets displayed here instead of the default message.
So that is essentially the functionality that we want.
So you could keep something secret from other people, and you would be able to authenticate yourself
as a user to be able to add it.
And then you need to be authenticated in order to view that secret.
There are a number of things that you need to do to achieve this.
The first to do is of course adding in that column.
And if I update this user's table, refresh it.
You'll see that brand new secret that I added just now going in right there.
And if you go ahead and open up the extracted 9.6 secrets project, and you take a look through the
index.js, you'll see that I've put in some to do's for you.
There's three to do's here.
You need to update the get route for secrets in order to pull in the secret that belongs to the user
if they have one.
And then you need to think about how to create a get route so that we can show people the submit Ejs
page and think about how we should only allow authenticated users to view that, submit a secret page,
and if they're not authenticated, they should be asked to log in.
And then finally, we need to create the post route for submit so that when a user does submit their
secret from here, that secret gets saved in the database and replaces anything that exists there before,
and finally makes sure that all of that process went through smoothly.
Now, a couple of things to note.
If you get confused, the SQL command that's required to update the column is in here.
But of course, given that you've already done the database module, you should already know how to
do that.
And this is a good point to test your knowledge.
And even if you don't remember, I recommend googling before looking at the solution.
See if you can figure it out first.
And the solution code, which we'll run through together, includes all of the to do's that needs to
happen before this code is going to work.
Final reminder in the dot env file, you need to replace your client secret and your client ID with
your own Google client ID and secret.
That way the Google login part will actually work.
So you should have this from the previous lesson and you can simply go and paste it in.
So now I'm going to leave you to it in your own capable hands, to struggle and to figure things out
and see if you can get this to work.
And finally, complete the Secrets Project.
I'll wait here, and once you come back, we'll talk through the solution together.
All right.
So the first thing I'm going to do is to put in my own values for the Google client ID and Google client
secret.
Next I'm going to go into the secrets dot js page.
And I'm going to update it so that instead of having that plain text, I'm replacing it with a JS tag.
So this is the angle bracket percentage equal.
And this is going to be sent in here programmatically.
If you don't know what I'm talking about in terms of JS in terms of partials, then be sure that you
haven't skipped a module on that in the course.
So now that I've done that, I can close that file down and I can focus on the to do's here.
The first thing I'm going to work on is creating a get route so that we can actually display the submit
page.
And this is going to be triggered when the user is on the secrets page and they click on this button,
submit a secret that's going to hit up the submit route.
And this is what it looks like in the browser.
So this is the button we're going to hook up to our server.
So we've got our App.get submit.
And then we're going to add our callback req res.
And then inside here we're going to think about how we're going to prevent an unauthorized user from
seeing the submit page.
So we know that the submit page is under submit JS.
But we should only render this if they are already logged in.
But thankfully, we know from our secrets route that we can simply use the request object to check to
see if the user is authenticated.
Because we're using passport and because we're using sessions and the user detail is saved in those
requests, that gets passed around.
So we can do the same thing and say if request dot is authenticated.
Well, in that case we're going to raise dot render submit dot js.
But otherwise we're going to raise dot redirect and take them back over to the login page like so that
is that to do done.
So I'm going to check that off.
Next I'm going to set up the post route for submit.
Once the user is on this submit page and they type a secret when they hit that submit button, it's
going to hit up our post route in our server because the form action goes to forward slash submit making
the request post.
So we have to write this right here.
And I'm going to write a App.post.
And the route is forward slash submit.
And then we add our request response etc..
And now inside this route we need to handle the submitted data and add it to the database.
We've already got body parser enabled in this, so we can simply set the secret to a const as the request
dot body.
And if we check here for that input, what is the name of that input.
Well it's just called secret.
So request dot body dot secret is going to equal whatever the user types in here.
And then we're going to submit that into our database.
Now how do we know under which user to submit this secret to in the database.
How do we know that it's this user that's logged in.
And we need to put the secret under their record?
Well, remember what I said previously about using passport?
One of the great benefits is we can get access to the user through request dot user.
And this is because when we do our login local strategy or when we do our Google login strategy, in
both cases, we return the user and all of their data in the callback, which gets serialized, and
then deserialized so that we can access them right here under Request.user.
So if you want, you can console, log and see the result of that.
Now I know that I can simply access the Request.user dot email and query it in my database.
So I'm going to do a try catch.
And I'm going to use my await and then db dot query.
And the query that I'm going to use is update users.
So update the table called users and set the field.
That's called secret to equal dollar one.
And I need to make sure that I'm only setting this for one user.
And that's where their email is equal to the second input dollar two.
So now let's put in dollar $1 $2 one is going to be equal to the secret.
And dollar two is going to be the request dot user dot email.
Now because this is asynchronous.
Let's go ahead and change this to async.
So that that works.
After all of that's done we're waiting for this to finish.
Hence the await.
And after that then we go ahead and do raise dot redirect and take the user to see their secret.
So we're going to redirect them to the secret route which is of course the get route, which means they
get to view the secrets dot JS, which we have one more to do to pull up their secret from the database.
So we've saved all of this and we have caught our error.
And I'm just going to, for simplicity sake, console log that error as my error handling for now.
So I'm done with the second to do.
And I'm going to replace my to do with a comment for you so you know how to find it.
And the last to do here is to change the app.get route for secrets, so that we actually pull in the
user's secret so that we can render it in the secret.
So JS remember, we already changed our secrets dot JS so that it now uses a Ejs tag to receive under
secret.
We have to get hold of that by passing it in in the same sentence as we do our rest render, our res
dot render happens and then we get to add some things to pass over.
In our case it's called secret.
And what is the secret that we're going to pass?
Well, we're going to have to get hold of that from our database.
Again.
We're going to do a try catch.
And what we're going to try to do is to create a const called result.
We're going to do await.
And then we do db dot query.
And the query that we're going to make is select the column called secret from the table called users.
And then the condition is where email equals dollar one.
And the email is again going to come from our passport authentication Request.user dot email.
And it's really neat being able to access the user's details at any point because of this whole passport
session thing that we've already set up.
So that's pretty neat.
And because we're using await, let's go ahead and change this to async as well.
And make sure that Request.user email is in a array.
I think I missed that out just now, so make sure you check yours.
So once we get the result, we're going to console log the result just so that you can see it.
But I know that it should contain a secret for the user that I just logged in.
I'm going to go ahead and continue to fetch that secret out of the result.
So it's going to be result dot rows at the row zero.
And then it's under the column called secret.
So this should allow me to access the secret.
If the secret exists we're going to go ahead and do what we plan to do, which is to render that secret
and pass it over like so.
But what if it's a user who doesn't have a secret yet?
They just join the website.
They don't have one.
Well, in this case we're going to raise dot render secrets dot js.
And we can put in the default which is Jack Bauer is my hero.
Alternatively you can just have a placeholder.
You should submit a secret.
It can be anything that you want.
And finally I'm going to catch the error here with just a console log.
And that should complete this to do.
Let me put a marker here.
And now let's go ahead and try it out.
So I'm going to log in as my user.
And you can see that the secret that I submitted previously still shows right here.
I'm going to click on Submit a Secret and let's try a new one.
Click submit and goes to test.
Let's try logging out and logging in again.
And you can see it's still persisted because it's pulling it in from our database.
So I hope you had fun building this application and in the process, learning all about authentication.
I've kept this project as simple as possible so that we can focus on the important things, which is
already complicated enough.
But this is a good time to try practicing what you've learned by applying these authentication steps
and knowledge to a previous project of your own.
So have a think about what you might want to do.
Brainstorm some projects and if you build anything cool.
As always, post in the Q&A.
I would love to hear about it.