Hi guys.
In this lesson I want to quickly talk through how to get hold of the course resources As you're working
through the course.
In many sections of the course, there will be downloadable resources and they are usually in a compressed
format.
So you'll see the.zip as the file extension.
Now what this means is that you can't use the files in this folder as it is.
You have to extract the files out of this folder and then once you've extracted it, you'll see that
the folder contains many resources such as images, or sounds, or other things that we're going to use
in the project, but also code files, which we're going to be using in order to complete some of the
exercises and projects.
So in order to download the course resources for a particular lesson, I want you to go into the resources
for that lesson, which should show up with a folder icon, click the down button and you'll see all
of the links that are included in that folder.
And in most cases the download will be a zip file.
So what I want you to do is to click on it and download should start automatically in your browser.
And then I want you to head over to your downloads folder,
and if you're on a Mac computer, then you can simply double-click on the zip file and it will automatically
extract all of the contents into a new folder.
Now on Windows, it's a little bit different.
All you have to do is to select the compressed file in your downloads folder and then you should see
at the top this extract all button show up.
If you don't see that, then simply just right click on the compressed folder and you should also be able
to find that extract all and then go ahead and simply select, extract and make a note of the destination.
Now once you've done that and you've gotten hold of the extracted folder and all of the files that it
contains, then I want you to simply drag it into your Visual Studio code and you'll see that VS Code
will automatically open up your folder and give you access to all of the included files.
If you try to drag a compressed folder into VS Code, it won't work properly and sometimes you might
be able to see the files, but you might not be able to work with it.
For example, on Windows you might be able to view the files, but it can create a lot of problems for
you down the road.
So remember, whenever you're downloading a file that has the.zip extension, be sure to extract the
files before you work with it in VS Code.