Well done
for completing the first module. You've already come so far just by taking the first step, because
you know that most people who buy online courses, they never get started.
So you're already one step closer to your goal.
But we all know that at some point later on, things will get more difficult.
It will get more challenging.
I can promise you this already.
So how can you keep this current level of motivation that you have and be able to carry it through to
the difficult times?
One of the things that I find really helpful is setting goals and having my goals around me, like displayed
on the wall while I'm working or while I'm studying.
So I've created this fantastic worksheet for you so that you can start thinking about why you're doing
this.
Why are you learning to code?
Why are you learning the skill?
What will you be able to achieve once you've mastered it?
And what would your life look like once that happens?
So head over to the next lesson,
fill out the sheet with your answers and then print it out and put it somewhere where you can see it
so that when things become difficult and when your motivation takes a nosedive, you can have a look
at it and remind yourself of why you're doing it in the first place.
So head over there now.